<DOC>
<DOCNO>1</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAD8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / (CORRECTED) Jubilee of a jet that did what it was designed
to do
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Correction (published 16th May 1991) appended to this article.
'FRANK, it flies]' shouted someone at Sir Frank Whittle during the maiden
flight of a British jet. 'Of course it does,' replied Sir Frank, who
patented the first aircraft gas turbine. 'That's what it was bloody well
designed to do, wasn't it?'
Exactly 50 years ago yesterday, the first British jet made a brief 17-minute
flight from RAF Cranwell in Lincolnshire. To celebrate the event, Mr Eric
'Winkle' Brown, a 72-year-old test pilot of the prototype Gloster Whittle
jet, Mr Geoffrey Bone, a 73-year-old engineer, and Mr Charles McClure, a
75-year-old pilot, returned to RAF Cranwell. They are seen in front of a
restored Meteor NF 11. Sir Frank was unable to attend because of ill-health.
The Gloster Whittle was not the first jet to fly: a Heinkel 178 had its
maiden flight in August 1939, 21 months before the British aircraft.
Correction (published 16th May 1991).
THE PICTURE of a Gloster Whittle jet on Page 7 of the issue of Tuesday May
14, was taken at Bournemouth Airport and not at RAF Cranwell as stated in
the caption.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7 Photograph (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>2</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQABQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / (CORRECTED) UK Company News: Geevor merger hits rocks over
pre-conditions
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING, Mining Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Correction (published 16th May 1991) appended to this article.
Geevor, the UK mining group which has been fighting for survival since the
Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce called in a Pounds 2.1m loan in
extraordinary circumstances in January, has suffered another set-back.
Its proposed merger with European Mining Finance, a Luxembourg-quoted
investment company, has run into problems and will not go ahead on the terms
announced in March.
Two of the pre-conditions for the merger have not been satisfied - the
raising of bank finance for the enlarged group and the termination of the
management agreement between EMF and its manager, Lion Mining Finance.
However, Geevor said it remained in talks with EMF and other parties 'which
may result in modified proposals'.
Monarch Resources, the UK-quoted mining group with operations in Venezuela,
has appointed Mr Anthony Ciali as president and chief executive officer.
This follows the recent boardroom shake-up which resulted in the departure
of seven directors and the arrival of Mr Michael Beckett as chairman.
Mr Beckett was managing director of Consolidated Gold Fields and Mr Ciali
was once a vice-president of Gold Fields Mining Corp, a US subsidiary.
Correction (published 16th May 1991).
Lion Mining Finance is not the manager of European Mining Finance as we
reported on May 14.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>3</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Contigas plans DM900m east
German project
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID GOODHART
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BONN
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
CONTIGAS, the German gas group 81 per cent owned by the utility Bayernwerk,
said yesterday that it intends to invest DM900m (Dollars 522m) in the next
four years to build a new gas distribution system in the east German state
of Thuringia.
Reporting on its results for 1989-1990 the company said that the dividend
would remain unchanged at DM8.
Sales rose 9.4 per cent to DM3.37bn, but post-tax profit fell slightly from
DM31.3m to DM30.7m.
In the first half of the current year sales rose 23 per cent.
Mr Jurgen Weber, currently vice-chairman of Lufthansa, the German airline,
is today expected to be named as the successor to the chairman Mr Heinz
Ruhnau who retires at the end of 1992.
Mr Weber is currently the technical director on the Lufthansa board.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>4</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Population warning
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The world's population is growing faster than predicted and will consume at
an unprecedented rate the natural resources required for human survival, a
UN report said.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>5</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Newspaper pays up
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
A Malaysian English-language newspaper agreed to pay former Singapore prime
minister Lee Kuan Yew Dollars 100,000 over allegations of corruption.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>6</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Khmer Rouge snub
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Khmer Rouge guerrillas refused a UN observer team's request for a visit to
the front line to observe the Cambodian ceasefire.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>7</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Cocaine ring broken
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Spanish police said they had broken up a cocaine-smuggling ring, arresting
15 Chileans and seizing Pta92m (Dollars 900,000) in cash.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>8</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AADFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Malawi frees poet
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Malawi has freed dissident poet Jack Mapanje, 46, detained without trial for
more than three years, Amnesty International said.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>9</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AACFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Booby-trap murder
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
A Northern Ireland businessman and senior member of the loyalist Orange
Order died when an IRA bomb exploded under his car in Armagh.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>10</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AABFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Brussels rioting
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Almost 200 North African immigrants were arrested in Brussels at the weekend
during the worst racial rioting ever seen in the normally placid Belgian
capital.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>11</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BEOA7AAAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World News in Brief: Soviet deadlock
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The Soviet parliament was deadlocked over a bill to guarantee the right to
travel abroad. Many deputies suggested authorities could not cope with a
flood of tourists and would-be emigrants.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
International Page 1
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>12</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / London Stock Exchange: FT-SE 2,500 lost in nervous trading
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
FRESH indications of the depth of the UK recession, wavering optimism for
base rate cuts this week and a poor lead from Wall Street all combined to
undermine the UK stock market yesterday.
Pressure for a further reduction in base rates was increased by the news
yesterday that the monthly rise in domestic consumer borrowing was at a
six-year low in March. However, last week's cautionary views on interest
rates from the Bank of England have cast uncertainty over hopes in the City
of London that UK base rates will be cut this Friday in the wake of the
expected fall in the UK retail price index.
Attempts by the equity market to hold on to FT-SE 2,500, reached at the end
of last month, proved fruitless yesterday and the market closed 37.7 points
down at 2,486.6. The final picture was exceedingly gloomy, with the London
market extending its losses to finish virtually at the day's low as Wall
Street continued its overnight fall of 51 Dow points by losing a further
9.39 early in the new session.
Confidence was not helped at the close by sudden rumours that another large
rights issue is in the offing. Institutional coffers are beginning to feel
the weight of a 1991 rights issue burden already approaching Pounds 4bn,
without including a substantial number of share placings.
In the face of Wall Street's heavy setback on Friday night, the London
market opened 23 Footsie points off, quickly abandoning the FT-SE 2,500 mark
attained at the close of business on April 30. There was no significant
recovery during the session but further losses were restrained at first by
the relative absence of sellers and a FT-SE June futures contract which
managed to hold above 2,500 until late in the day. But losses in share
prices were rapidly extended in late trading as the big institutions backed
away from the stock market.
Market volume, as recorded by a Seaq-traded shares total of 354.9m shares,
was low, even by comparison with Friday's 423m figure. The institutions were
believed to be top slicing, selling a small part of their holdings in blue
chip stocks in the expectation that these shares will be bought back more
cheaply in the weeks ahead.
Weakness in oil shares set the trend for widespread losses among Wall
Street-orientated stocks. The industrial blue chips featured falls in BOC,
BAT Industries, Reuters and ICI. However, share losses in the international
sector were mostly suffered early in the session and did not increase
disproportionately after Wall Street opened lower; some analysts commented
that this indicated that domestic factors were the most significant in the
market yesterday.
The uncertain political scene in the UK, ahead of Thursday's by-election in
the Monmouth constituency acted as a further discouragement to the big
institutions, which are increasingly of the view that there will be little
to attract them to the UK stock market until the third quarter of the year.
Trading specialists suggested yesterday that, with their cash holdings
drained by rights issues, the institutions are now less willing to buy cheap
stock whenever the market gives ground. Some believe that fund managers may
wait until the FT-SE falls by a further 50 or more points before making
serious buying forays.
However, optimism for a further strong rise in the UK market over the next
12 months, perhaps to around FT-SE 2,750, remains undimmed.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 40
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>13</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / London Stock Exchange: Equity Futures and Options Trading
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
LONDON derivatives continued to trade under the shadow of Wall Street,
opening weaker following the decline in the US in the previous session and
then slipping still lower as New York extended its slide in London hours
yesterday.
The UK equity futures market began weakly and helped to pull the stock
market down. The premium of the June FT-SE 100 index over the spot index
narrowed from 20 points to around 10 on selling by independent traders.
At one stage, the futures market attempted to rally and succeeded in
widening the gap over the share market to 20 points. But with Wall Street on
the defensive, prices were again marked lower and by the close June was back
to less than a 10-point premium to the spot market.
The June FT-SE closed at 2,494, down 42 points on the day. Its premium
finished at 6 points, against fair value of 15.
In traded options, the stock market's inability to break out of the range of
the past fortnight prompted investors to sell calls against stock holdings.
Elsewhere, there was a buyer of 1,000 Asda July 130 calls; a buyer of 500
GrandMet October 650 puts; and a buyer of 250 Barclays June 460 calls.
The Euro FT-SE was boosted by a seller of 1,000 July 2,625 calls and a buyer
of 1,000 July 2,525 puts.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 40
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>14</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / World Stock Markets (America): Bond recovery fails to bring
joy to equities
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
Wall Street
THE STOCK market remained subdued yesterday in the wake of last Friday's
sell-off, with the Dow Jones Industrial Average rallying only marginally in
very light trading from the 50-point drop, writes Patrick Harverson in New
York.
At the close the Dow was 4.25 up at 2,924.42, having spent most of the day
in negative territory. The more broadly based Standard &amp; Poor's 500 moved in
similar fashion, recovering 1.02 on balance at 376.76, while the Nasdaq
composite picked up 0.51 to 493.93. Turnover on the New York SE totalled
just 130m shares, while rises showed a small lead over falls at the finish
by 786 to 742.
On Friday it was the sharp fall in bond values which led share prices lower,
but yesterday's modest recovery in the bond market failed to stimulate a
similar movement among stocks. The weakness in the US economy continues to
trouble investors, who can see little reason to invest more of their money
in equities.
Yesterday's industrial production data provided no real comfort on the
economic front. Although the data showed an expected 0.1 per cent increase
in April production, the Federal Reserve also revealed a revised 0.6 per
cent decline in March production, previously estimated at 0.3 per cent.
Banks featured, with American Express dropping Dollars 1 1/4 to Dollars 22
3/4 on turnover of 4.1m shares after announcing that it would take a Dollars
144m pre-tax charge to account for the 28 per cent stake held by Shearson
Lehman Brothers, its securities subsidiary, in First Capital Holdings, the
troubled Californian life insurance group.
Bankers Trust was down Dollars 1 at Dollars 48 5/8 after the New York-based
banking group confirmed it was laying off 200 staff, while JP Morgan, which
had been actively bought since it was announced over a week ago that the
stock would join the Dow index, slipped Dollars 1 1/2 to Dollars 50 3/8 on
meeting profit-taking.
Square D jumped Dollars 6 3/8 to Dollars 87 3/8 after the company agreed to
the bid by Schneider, of France, of Dollars 88 a share, or Dollars 2.23bn.
AT&amp;T bucked the trend, firming Dollars  5/8 to Dollars 36 1/2 in active
trading after reports that the merger with NCR is proceeding faster than
expected.
On the over-the-counter market, Nordstrom jumped Dollars 2 3/4 to Dollars 44
on turnover of 1.5m shares on the back of an improvement of almost 100 per
cent in first-quarter profits. Apple Computer climbed Dollars 1 1/2 to
Dollars 52 3/4 on volume of 2.2m shares after the company introduced its
System 7 operating system software and said it would cut prices on logic
board upgrades and memory kits for the Macintosh.
Metcalf &amp; Eddy fell Dollars 1 1/2 to Dollars 15 1/4 after the water
treatment and waste management company issued a second-quarter profits
warning.
Canada
AFTER spending most of the day in lower territory, the Toronto market
managed a mild recovery during the afternoon to end on a mixed note.
The composite index was finally a net 2.9 up at 3,492.7 but declining issues
still held an edge over advances by 273 to 240. Volume amounted to 21.6m
shares, down from Friday's 23.3m.
Lincoln Waste Management topped the most actives list after one of the
company's largest shareholders and one of its directors sold more than 4m
shares, approaching one-fifth of the session's moderate volume. The share
price was steady at CDollars 10 7/8 .
John Labatt, which rose CDollars 1 to CDollars 23 5/8 , said it is
considering selling its JL Foods Inc unit.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 37
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>15</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Foreign Exchanges: Dollar and yen lose ground
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
THE DOLLAR fell against European currencies but improved in terms of the
Japanese yen yesterday. A rise of 0.1 per cent in April US industrial
production was roughly in line with expectations, while a revised fall of
0.6 per cent from 0.3 per cent in March output brought little reaction in
the US currency.
A decline to 78.3 per cent in April US capacity utilisation, from a downward
revision to 78.5 per cent for March, also had no effect on a market waiting
for today's data on US consumer prices and Friday's trade figures.
At the London close the dollar had fallen to DM1.7140 from DM1.7255; to
FFr5.8050 from FFr5.8400; and to SFr1.4430 from SFr1.4580. On the other hand
it rose to Y139.40 from Y138.75 against a generally weak yen. The dollar's
index dipped to 66.2 from 66.4.
Speculation about an early cut in the Bank of Japan's discount rate
depressed the yen. This helped to boost the D-Mark after rumours subsided
that Mr Karl Otto Pohl was about to resign as president of the German
Bundesbank.
The rumours led to D-Mark nervousness in early trading, but by the end of
the day attention was focused on interest rate factors and this pushed the
German currency up against the yen. It finished in London at Y81.35 compared
with Y80.40 on Friday.
In the European exchange rate mechanism the D-Mark improved against the
weakest placed French franc and also the Italian lira, but lost ground to
sterling.
The Bank of France left its money market intervention rate unchanged at 9
per cent at a securities repurchase tender, keeping interest rate
differentials steady as the Bank of Spain and Belgian National Bank also
left rates unaltered at similar tenders.
The lira weakened against several of its partners in the ERM after Sunday's
one-point cut to 11 1/2 per cent in the Bank of Italy's discount rate.
However, it remained the second strongest ERM currency, according to figures
from the European Commission, in spite of losing ground to the D-Mark,
French franc and other members of the ERM at the Milan fixing.
Sterling was the third strongest ERM currency as speculation continued about
the possible timing of another reduction in UK bank base rates. Mr David
Mellor, chief secretary to the Treasury, said on BBC radio that 'the
chancellor will not cut interest rates until he considers it prudent to do
so'.
The Bank of England has signalled that it does not consider this an
appropriate time, but the market still believes an early cut is possible as
political pressure increases on the government.
Sterling rose 1.30 cents to Dollars 1.7320, while improving to DM2.9675 from
DM2.9650; to Y241.50 from Y238.50; and to FFr10.0550 from FFr10.0400, but it
eased to SFr2.5000 from SFr2.5075. The pound's index put on 0.2 to 91.8.
Sterling gained a further 20 points in New York to end at Dollars 1.7340.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 31
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>16</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Commodities and Agriculture: Farmers' Viewpoint - Machinery
rings seem an all-round success story / The time is coming in the UK for a
co-operative idea already working very well on the Continent
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Farmers love government grants. But the flurry of urgent activity in recent
weeks to beat today's deadline for applications for grant aid to help set up
machinery rings has been out of all proportion to their value. There are
much more significant reasons for farmers to co-operate in an effort to cut
the capital costs of machinery. The ending of the modest Pounds 10,000 per
ring grant payable over three years merely concentrated minds.
Machinery rings began in Germany about 25 years ago. Born out of hard times,
they brought together groups of farmers in local areas who were prepared to
work some of their machinery on other people's farms where the appropriate
tackle was worn out or did not exist. In other words, one member of a ring
might provide the combine harvester and deal with the grain on a number of
farms while another would bale the straw and yet another might plough and
plant all the land for the following year's crops.
Rings formalised local arrangements of this kind which had been going on
between farmers in the same village for years and set standard charges for
given tasks. By broadening the area over which such arrangements operated,
it also gave members access to more specialised equipment. By employing a
manager to co-ordinate the work it provided organisation and a guarantee of
payment to those who did the work.
Today, there are about 260 machinery rings in Germany and the idea has
spread to other European countries, especially Holland and France. There
were no rings established in the UK, however, until 1987 after a visit to
Germany by a Scottish agricultural adviser who came home and enthused his
clients over the concept. Since then, 10 machinery rings have been set up in
Scotland.
Although most are still developing and expanding, it is expected that the
total turnover of the Scottish rings this year will reach Pounds 2.5m.
Moreover, the single most successful Scottish group, with 220 members
already, has a turnover in excess of Pounds 1m.
The first English machinery ring was formed in Sussex and Kent only last
year. Since then, 15 more have been established across the country. All have
or are hoping to qualify for the Pounds 10,000 grant, 25 per cent of which
comes from the EC and 75 per cent from the UK government. The scheme is
administered by Food From Britain. At least another two rings are thought to
be in course of formation but they will almost certainly not meet today's
grant deadline.
Within four years, therefore, Britain has gone from no machinery rings to
close to 30 and the majority of them have been set up during the last few
weeks. The ending of the grant had undoubtedly speeded their formation (it
has been available since 1986) but Pounds 3,333 per year for three years
split be-tween perhaps 200-300 farmers is insufficient motivation on its own
for what has happened.
The plain fact is that the machinery ring is an idea whose time has now come
in the UK. To some extent there is an element of following fashion because
the concept has received a great deal of publicity in recent months. The
main reason for the rush of activity, however, is declining farm profits and
the realisation by a growing number of farmers that they must cut their
costs to survive in business.
On average, the so-called 'variable costs' of running a farm - the money
spent on seeds, fertilisers, sprays and so on - amount to between 35 per
cent and 40 per cent of total costs. Fixed costs account for the remaining
60 per cent to 65 per cent and cover such things as labour, interest
charges, power and machinery.
In recent years, as margins have declined, some of these 'fixed costs' have
had to become variable as numbers of farmworkers have diminished either
through natural wastage or redundancy and as assets have been sold to reduce
borrowings and, therefore, interest charges. Power costs are more difficult
to control in the face of fluctuating oil prices while real depreciation on
machinery values can be horrendous.
Indeed, the depreciation rates typically used in farm accounts may well be
insufficient to allow for the replacement of machines whose purchase prices
continue to rise with inflation.
Add to that the fact that many farms are over-mechanised for the
understandable reason that farmers like to feel on top of any job, whatever
the weather, and it is clear that economies in machinery costs are overdue
in the current financial climate.
The machinery ring has obviously been recognised as a possible solution. For
Pounds 50 per year membership charge and a modest purchase of share capital,
a farmer can plug into a source of extra income or extra help, whichever he
prefers. Commission charges of 2 per cent are levied on both the demander
and the provider of the work to cover the costs of the co-ordinator and his
computer. Otherwise, the charges for work are set at similar rates to the
most competitive contractors.
Experience shows, apparently, that most rings lose money in their first year
or two but that as the organisation develops and as members begin to review
their machinery replacement policies, the flow of work offered and done
builds up dramatically. Indeed, it is possible to foresee situations where
some farmers decide to buy bigger machines than they can justify in order to
earn extra cash working on other members' farms. At the same time, other
farmers may see opportunities to earn more money off the farm and be pleased
to pay a ring member to do most of his farm work.
The pattern is already established in Germany, albeit on smaller farms than
are typical in the UK. It is yet another step towards the establishment of
significant numbers of part-time farmers in this country. In any event,
those groups of farmers who have their machinery rings up and running are
convinced that there is a potential for many more.
A couple of weeks ago, there was a meeting of machinery ring leaders at the
National Agricultural Centre at Stoneleigh, in Warwickshire. They decided to
set up an Association of Machinery Rings to guide those who come after and
to lobby on behalf of members on such things as the presently-restricted use
of red, tax-free diesel fuel in tractors travelling more than 15 miles from
their home base. They see this as a possible inhibition to the efficient
working of rings which may cover an area 30 to 40 miles wide.
The success of the concept relies on the willing co-operation of farmers. In
this country, agricultural co-operation, with a few notable exceptions, has
seldom succeeded beyond the first flush of enthusiasm. I believe this
machinery ring version of co-operation will work. In any case, the other day
I signed up to join one.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30 Illustration (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>17</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Commodities and Agriculture: LME monitors copper market as
squeeze tightens
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING, Mining Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE LONDON Metal Exchange executive yesterday said it was carefully
monitoring events in the copper market where a technical squeeze has been
causing severe volatility.
As the squeeze reached its climax yesterday the price of borrowing (buying
cash and selling forward) for one day reached Pounds 40 a tonne.
During recent upheavals in the zinc market, the LME executive persuaded
those with metal to lend to restrict the cost of borrowing for a day to
Dollars 20 a tonne and some dealers asked last night why the cost of
borrowing copper had been allowed to rise much more substantially.
Mr Martin Abbott, the LME's director of marketing, said: 'Our duty is to run
an orderly market - not to limit the cost of borrowing or the back-wardation
(the premium for metal for immediate delivery compared with the three-month
price).'
Copper's backwardation widened to Pounds 100 a tonne at one stage yesterday
and traders said this would continue to stimulate a flood of the metal into
LME warehouse stocks. Copper stocks already stood at 261,775 tonnes at the
weekend, the highest total for seven years, and traders estimated that
today's stock report would show a further increase of about 10,000 tonnes.
Mr Abbott said however, that, although the LME's copper stocks were
relatively high, it would be wrong to assume that all the metal was
available to be sold on the market. The owners might well be 'parking' the
copper briefly in LME warehouses.
The copper market was going through a 'choppy period' of volatility because
there was still a split of opinion about whether there would be a surplus
this year, Mr Abbott suggested. This choppiness could go on for some time
before there was a clear consensus of opinion about the fundamental
direction of the market.
However, many analysts now insist that the recession which is begining to
make its mark on even the strongest economies will far outweigh any
interruptions to copper supplies this year.
In the latest Metals and Mining Monthly Update from Carr Kitcat &amp; Aitken,
part of the Banque Indosuez Group, analyst Mr Robin Bhar says key copper
consuming sectors in the US (construction, autos and capital goods) will
remain depressed and consumption in Germany is likely to be restrained by
slowing economic growth caused by the mounting costs of reunification.
Consequently, says Mr Bhar, copper stocks will keep rising during 1991 and
the price is likely to fall decisively below Dollars 1 a lb, perhaps to
between 70 cents and 80 cents a lb. The dollar price ended at Dollars 1.04 a
lb last night.
In sterling terms, cash copper ended at Pounds 1,443 a tonne, down Pounds
6.50 from Friday's close, while three-month metal was Pounds 1,346, down
Pounds 11.50.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>18</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAGAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Commodities and Agriculture: Total in Algerian gas field
deal
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
TOTAL, THE French state-controlled oil group, has signed a FFr3bn (Dollars
512m) agreement with Sonatrach, Algeria's state oil company, for the
development of the Hamra gas field, writes George Graham in Paris.
The French group will provide financing and technological assistance for the
development of the field, expected to start production in 1994.
In return, Total will have access to Hamra's entire output of condensates
and liquefied petroleum gas - an estimated 150m to 200m barrels petroleum
equivalent - for a period of 14 to 17 years.
The deal shows the continued willingness of big Western companies to invest
in Algeria, despite the political uncertainty that has been hanging over the
country's future since the rise of the fundamentalist Islamic Salvation
Front.
Total also agreed yesterday to renew for a further five years its joint
venture with Sonatrach for the operation of the Mereksen oil field, which
currently produces around 600,000 tonnes of oil a year. It also signed two
exploration contracts covering 6,458 square kilometres at Djebel Bottena and
Hamra Southeast.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>19</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Commodities and Agriculture: Fuel cell use is predicted for
platinum
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KENNETH GOODING, Mining Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FUEL CELLS, environmentally friendly units which produce electricity and
heat from a controlled chemical reaction be-tween hydrogen and oxygen, are
likely to provide the next substantial industrial application for platinum,
according to Johnson Matthey, the world's biggest platinum marketing group.
By the end of this century about 200,000 troy ounces of platinum a year
could be ab-sorbed by this new market - about the same as the chemical and
electrical industries each use today, JM suggests in its annual review of
the market.
However, this could be a conservative estimate. If fuel cells incorporating
platinum catalysts are used and if the market develops as projected by the
Japanese Ministry of International Trade and Industry, annual demand for
platinum in that country alone by the year 2010 would be more than 400,000
ounces.
'Beyond the turn of the century platinum consumption could soar, should the
market for fuel cells in vehicles materialise and dreams of a hydrogen
economy become a reality,' says Mr Jeremy Coombes, author of the JM review.
The fuel cell is a prime contender to meet demand for electricity without
increasing pollution, he points out. It is versatile and efficient, produces
hardly any noxious emissions and so could help to re-solve the apparent
conflict between continued economic growth and the preservation of a healthy
environment.
Fuel cells went into commercial production for the first time last year.
Japan is showing the most commitment to their development. The Japanese
government is spending about Dollars 27m a year on research, and Fuji
Electric, Toshiba and Sanyo have developed marketable products and
established production lines to build them.
The US Department of Energy is currently spending Dollars 44m a year on fuel
cell research while spending in Europe is about Dollars 60m. By 1995 more
than 100 fuel cells will be installed and producing power in Europe, Japan,
the US and the Far East.
Mr Coombes says commercial units should be available in 1993 at a cost of
Dollars 1,500 per kilowat of generating capacity, not much more than the
cost from conventional generating plant, and the cost is likely to fall as
more fuel cells are built.
On the main features of the platinum market last year, the JM review
reports:
Demand for platinum in-creased by 5.5 per cent to a record 3.66m ounces.
Supplies rose by 9 per cent to 3.73m ounces.
The market moved into marginal oversupply of 70,000 ounces from a marginal
undersupply of 45,000 ounces in 1989. The slight oversupply might continue
for some years.
Supplies from South Africa, the world's biggest producer, were constrained
by production difficulties but grew modestly. Shipments to the west from the
Soviet Union, at 700,000 ounces, were the highest for 15 years.
This year JM expects platinum to trade at about Dollars 400 an ounce before
rising as the year progresses towards Dollars 450.
'Platinum 1991', free from Johnson Matthey, 78 Hatton Garden House, London
EC1N 8JP, England.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30 Chart (Omitted). Graph (Omitted). Photograph Humbug Machine,
a Rowland Emett model powered by a fuel cell containing platinum catalysts
(Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>20</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Capital Markets: Citicorp in asset-backed
launch worth Dollars 1.4bn
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SIMON LONDON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
CITICORP yesterday launched its first global asset-backed bond issue since
August last year, a Dollars 1.4bn deal backed by a portfolio of credit card
receivables.
The progress of the deal confirmed that investors are once again willing to
buy asset-backed securities. This will encourage other financial
institutions looking to remove consumer finance assets from their balance
sheets through securitised bond offerings.
The five-year deal, lead-managed by Salomon Brothers, is backed by credit
card receivables in Citicorp's 'master trust' of credit card accounts.
The main portion of the deal, at Dollars 1.25bn, carries a triple-A credit
rating by virtue of an additional Dollars 155m subordinated tranche which
will absorb any initial losses of the master trust.
The deal will be priced today, with the senior notes at an indicated yield
spread of between 95 and 99 basis points over five-year US Treasury paper.
The subordinated bonds, which carry an A-2/A credit rating from US credit
rating agencies Moody's and Standard &amp; Poor's, will be priced at around 145
basis points over US Treasuries.
The lead manager said most of the international market tranche of the deal
was placed with institutional investors based in London. However, US
investors remain dominant buyers of mortgage-backed bonds, and most of the
subordinated paper was placed in the US.
Citicorp's last asset-backed deal in the international bond market was
launched in November. The deal was then priced to yield 90 basis points over
US Treasury securities, but the bonds traded out to well over 100 basis
points after launch.
Market sentiment, however, has been firmer over the past two months, and the
deal's pricing was considered attractive. In addition, the deal had been
widely anticipated in the market, and many investors had set aside funds to
buy the bonds. Demand was dominated by institutional investors.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 29
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>21</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Government Bonds: Gilts follow Treasuries' fall in auction
aftermath
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SARA WEBB, PATRICK HARVERSON and DAVID LASCELLES, Banking Editor
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   LONDON, NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
UK GOVERNMENT bonds plummeted yesterday morning, responding to the sharp
fall in the US Treasury bond market on Friday afternoon.
The benchmark 11 3/4 per cent Treasury stock due 2003/07 opened at 110 9/32
and fell to a low of 109 1/2 before recovering in the afternoon.
Traders said the disappointing UK credit business figures released
yesterday, which were slightly higher than market expectations, may have
helped to depress prices.
The gilts market is this week waiting for the release of several important
economic indicators which could determine whether the Bank of England
decides to cut the base rate. These include the producer prices index for
April today, the unemployment figures on Thursday, and the retail prices
index on Friday.
THE US government bond market remained unsettled yesterday in the wake of
Friday's frenzied sell-off, but prices at the long end did gain ground on
the back of some sporadic buying.
In late trading, the benchmark 30-year Treasury issue was up 1 7/32 at 98
13/32 , to yield 8.264 per cent. The two-year note was up  1/16 at 100 5/16
, yielding 6.808 per cent. Trading activity was exceptionally light.
Dealers and investors continued to digest the implications of the dramatic
fall in prices which followed last week's difficult auction of Dollars 37bn
in government securities. With a large chunk of that paper still to be
distributed, analysts were not expecting any significant recovery in bond
values in the near term.
The day's only economic news had little impact on sentiment. The Federal
Reserve reported that industrial production rose 0.1 per cent in April,
after falling a revised 0.6 per cent in March.
THE Italian government bond market jumped yesterday following the
one-percentage point cut in the discount rate at the weekend.
The cut, from 12.5 to 11.5 per cent, followed the cabinet's approval of
L14,000bn in spending cuts and revenue increases to curb the public deficit.
Yields fell across the range of maturities as retail buyers scrambled to buy
bonds. The yield on the 12.5 per cent bond due 2001 fell from 13.35 per cent
to 13.07 per cent.
The Bank of Italy's decision to cut the reserve requirement on the net
increase in banks' and credit institutions' foreign currency deposits, with
effect from the June reserve month, was seen as a bullish factor by the
market. The move should free around L5,000bn of funds for use by the credit
system.
The cut in the Italian discount rate buoyed hopes of interest rate cuts in
the Spanish and French government bond markets
The Spanish bond market saw strong buying interest among the shorter-dated
maturities. The yield on Spain's 13.45 per cent government bond due April
1996 fell from 11.91 to 11.82 per cent as foreign buyers moved in, hoping to
benefit from an expected cut in the intervention rate.
The Bank of Spain left its key money market rate unchanged at 13.5 per cent
at its repurchase tender for central bank certificates. Traders said that
this was disappointing, but did not rule out the possibility of an interest
rate cut soon.
Other European government bond markets opened weak in the wake of the US
Treasury bond market's fall on Friday.
The German market was haunted yet again by the rumour that Bundesbank
president, Mr Karl Otto Pohl, may step down. Bund prices fell after the US
decline, with the longer maturities taking the brunt of the fall. Despite
some buying interest in short and medium-dated bunds, they ended almost
unchanged on the day.
JAPANESE government bonds rallied as a fall in short-term interest rates
rekindled hopes of a cut in the official discount rate.
The overnight unsecured call rate was cut from 8 3/16 to 8 1/16 per cent,
while the rate on three-month certificates of deposit fell from 7.9 to 7.83
per cent. The fall was interpreted by some traders as a possible sign of the
Bank of Japan easing monetary policy. The yen weakened against the dollar
due to the lower interest rates, and traders said the Bank of Japan
intervened to buy yen and sell dollars yesterday.
The bond rally was short-lived, and JGB prices closed almost unchanged as
attention later in the day focused on a number of Euroyen issues, including
one of Y50bn by the World Bank. The benchmark No 129 JGB opened with a yield
of 6.635 per cent, moving to 6.605 per cent before closing in Tokyo at 6.63.
Barclays de Zoete Wedd, the investment banking arm of the Barclays group,
has obtained a seat on the Frankfurt Stock Exchange through its
newly-acquired German investment bank, Merck, Finck, writes David Lascelles,
Banking Editor.
Skandinaviska Enskilda Banken (S-E-Banken) will use the trading name
Scandinvanian Bank for its branch in London. S-E-Banken bought Scandinavian
Banking Group, the London consortium bank, last year and its licence is
being surrendered.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28 Table (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>22</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: USF&amp;G to bolster capital by
Dollars 300m stock issues
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
USF&amp;G, the large but troubled US insurance group, yesterday revealed plans
to bolster its capital base by raising up to Dollars 300m through issues of
convertible preferred stock.
Last month, the Baltimore-based multiline insurer said that it would cut its
workforce by around a quarter in a major 'downsizing' of its business.
It is also in the midst of reorganising its operational structure so that
its commercial and personal lines become two separate businesses with
independent profit centres.
The company announced a Dollars 569m loss last year, and has already cut its
quarterly dividend from 73 cents a share to 5 cents a share.
A new chairman, Mr Norman Blake, was brought into the company in November,
and other management changes have followed.
USF&amp;G said yesterday that the majority of the proceeds of the new issues
would be used 'to strengthen the surplus of the primary unit, United States
Fidelity and Guaranty Company'.
It anticipated that the funds would be raised via the issue of two series of
convertible prefered stock. These would be sold to investors both through a
public offering and through a separate private placement.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>23</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Toyoda machinery sales surge
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROBERT THOMSON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   TOKYO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
TOYODA Automatic Loom Works, a leading member of the Toyota Motor group,
reported an 11.1 per cent increase in pre-tax profit to Y30.2bn (Dollars
218.84m) for the year to end-March, as sales of automobile assembly
equipment rose with the expansion of vehicle production at Toyota.
The company, the first founded of the Toyota group, reported an 18.8 per
cent increase in sales to Y583.69bn, with a 33.5 per cent surge in textile
machinery sales, a 28.2 per cent rise in automobile assembly equipment, and
an 8.8 per cent improvement in industrial vehicles.
Company officials said personnel expenses rose during the year because of
Japan's labour shortage, and earnings were affected by the increase in the
country's interest rates, but they added that the advance in sales more than
compensated for those costs.
However, Japan's vehicle market has softened and export markets are also
troubled, so sales for this year are expected to rise only 4.5 per cent to
Y610bn, while pre-tax profit is predicted to fall 2.3 per cent to Y29.5bn,
the first fall in five years.
Toyota Tsusho, a trading arm of the Toyota group, reported a 10.8 per cent
lift in sales to Y2,163bn, while pre-tax profit increased 4.5 per cent to
Y16.16bn.
Domestic sales advanced 10.4 per cent, while foreign trade increased 11.6
per cent, with exports up 19 per cent, imports down 0.5 per cent, and trade
between third world countries up 16.4 per cent.
The company expects a 6.2 per cent increase in sales to Y2,300bn this year
and an 11.4 per cent rise in pre-tax profit to Y18bn, despite higher labour
costs and a heavier interest payment burden.
Another Toyota affiliate, Aisin Seiki, is expecting a decline in recurring
profit from the Y20.2bn in the year to end-March, up 1.1 per cent on 1989,
to around Y17bn for the present year.
The company announced yesterday that sales for the year to end-March rose
14.5 per cent to Y525bn, with those of automobile parts up 14.8 per cent to
Y495.7bn and household machinery rising 10.1 per cent to Y29.2bn.
Sales for the current year are expected to increase 4.7 per cent to Y550bn,
but the expected downturn in profits is attributed to the sluggish car
market, and increased depreciation and personnel expenses.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>24</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Nordstrom boosts earnings
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KAREN ZAGOR
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
NORDSTROM, the Seattle-based retailer managed by the founding Nordstrom
family, yesterday turned in sharply higher first-quarter earnings and said
it had settled federal and state securities class action lawsuits for
Dollars 7.5m.
Mr John Goesling, Nordstrom's senior vice-president, said the results
'compare favourably with what we regarded as a disappointing performance
during the previous year's first quarter.'
Net income leapt 95 per cent to Dollars 25.7m, or 31 cents a share, from
Dollars 13.2m, or 16 cents, a year earlier. Net sales grew 10 per cent in
the three months to Dollars 610.6m from Dollars 555m.
Shares in Nordstrom jumped Dollars 2 3/4 to Dollars 44 yesterday in active
over-the-counter trading. The company attributed its improved performance to
improving sales trends, better management of inventories and steps taken in
the previous year to reduce operating expenses.
During the quarter, Nordstrom reduced its selling, general and
administrative expenses to 27.65 per cent of sales from 29.4 per cent a year
earlier.
Pre-tax earnings jumped 101 per cent to Dollars 41.4m, or 6.77 per cent of
sales, from Dollars 20.6m, or 3.71 per cent of sales, a year earlier.
Nordstrom also said yesterday that it had settled a number of lawsuits
alleging that the company and six of its officers failed to disclose that
Nordstrom might be liable for additional employee compensation arising from
Nordstrom's past employee practices.
In the last year, Nordstrom's reputation has been clouded by a union dispute
and by revelations that the company's commission sales force is not properly
compensated.
Mr Goesling said: 'While we have not yet resolved with our insurance company
their share of this settlement, we are confident that any payment made by
the company will not have a material effect on the results of operations for
the year.'
The settlement, which is subject to court approval, provides for payment of
Dollars 7.5m to shareholders who bought Nordstrom stock between February 1
1988 and March 8 1990.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>25</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Two Venezuelan airlines register
losses
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOE MANN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CARACAS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE TWO state-owned Venezuelan airlines due to be privatised this year
suffered financial losses in 1990, according to figures published by the
Ministry of Transportation and Communications.
Viasa, the government's international flag-carrier, lost USDollars 34m in
1990 on overall revenues of Dollars 268m, compared with Dollars 4.6m profit
in 1989 on revenues of Dollars 266.7m.
Another state-owned airline, Aeropostal, which flies domestic and
international routes, suffered a 1990 loss of Dollars 7.3m on revenues of
Dollars 82.1m.
In 1989, Aeropostal reported net earnings of Dollars 2.8m on revenues which
totalled Dollars 68.8m. (Dollar figures were calculated using free-market
exchange rates for the Venezuelan bolivar at the end of each year.)
The government of President Carlos Andres Perez is keen to privatise Viasa
and Aeropostal this year to demonstrate that its slow-moving privatisation
programme is finally getting off the ground.
Since the government took office over two years ago, it has privatised only
two commercial banks from a long list of companies it plans to sell off.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>26</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: SA Brewing expands in US water
heating
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
SA BREWING Holdings, the diversified Adelaide-based brewing and
manufacturing group, yesterday said it had more than doubled its share of
the US water heater market through the USDollars 31.65m acquisition of
Mor-Flo Industries.
SA Brewing said the acquisition would give it 30 per cent of the US market
for mains pressure water heaters, which accounts for around 7.6m units a
year.
The group entered the US water heaters market in 1989 thorough the purchase
of Bradford-White Corporation of Michigan, which claimed around 12 per cent
of the market.
The deal, which is subject to US regulatory approval, is expected to be
concluded in August.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>27</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Fletcher Challenge shares placed
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By TERRY HALL
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WELLINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
FLETCHER Challenge (FCL) yesterday announced it had successfully placed
NZDollars 195m (USDollars 115m) worth of shares with international
institutional investors in a move designed to ease its debt burden.
However, the company did not announce the fate of a further 25m shares which
were being offered as oversubscriptions and were not underwritten. It is
hoped these shares would raise the total to NZDollars 292.5m.
News of the unexpected placement forced the share prices sharply lower
yesterday, ending a month-long rally. FCL dropped 22 cents to NZDollars
3.92, which was 2 cents above the placement price for the 50m shares. The
placement was underwritten by brokers CS First Boston NZ and Potter Warburg
Markets.
Mr Hugh Fletcher, FCL chief executive officer, said the placement showed
international investors strongly supported the New Zealand company which has
diverse holdings in the forestry products and building materials industries.
An FCL spokesman said the additional funds would represent a reduction in
group debt levels of about 1.4 per cent.
The company last month revised its forecasts, warning that full-year profits
might be about 10 per cent below the NZDollars 662.4m for the year to June
30 1990.
FCL, the second largest newsprint producer in the world, has suffered from
declining demand for its paper and a drop in prices for pulp and timber.
The spokesman said capital spending peaked last year at NZDollars 1.3bn and
was expected to fall to about NZDollars 800m. He said the group had to sell
all its property interests, valued at about NZDollars 500m held through
Fletcher Construction and Challenge Properties.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>28</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAF0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Aerolneas Argentinas sale enters
final phase
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN BARHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BUENOS AIRES
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE privatisation of Aerolneas Argentinas, the Argentine national airline,
entered its final phase yesterday, six months after the government and an
international consortium exchanged contracts.
The consortium, led by Spain's Iberia, delivered Dollars 810m-worth of
foreign debt certificates to the government as part of an agreement reached
between the two sides in April.
The privatisation stalled earlier this year after the government and
consortium members squabbled over the terms of the contract. The buyers
refused to pay, while the government refused to deliver the 85 per cent of
Aerolineas shares on sale.
Under the new agreement, the consortium agreed to deliver Dollars 1.61bn in
foreign debt paper in two tranches. It has also provided satisfactory
guarantees from international banks underpinning its Dollars 540m investment
plan in Aerolneas, as required by the original contract.
Earlier, the buyers paid Dollars 142m in government dollar-denominated bonds
worth 68 per cent of face value on the local market, replacing Dollars 130m
in deferred payments due under the original contract.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>29</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Labatt to reduce its food
processing operations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BERNARD SIMON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   TORONTO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
JOHN LABATT, the Canadian food and beverage group, is putting a large part
of its food processing business up for sale in keeping with its strategy of
concentrating on beer, entertainment and dairy products.
Labatt, which is 39 per cent owned by the Brascan group controlled by Peter
and Edward Bronfman, said yesterday it will consider offers for Oregon-based
JLFoods, which specialises in frozen grocery products in Canada, the US and
Britain. JLFoods is the leading supplier of frozen soup in the US, and also
a large supplier of breaded and battered products.
The company has annual sales of USDollars 475m and employs 3,500 people at
13 manufacturing and processing plants, most of them in the US.
Analysts said the sale could fetch about USDollars 300m. The company, which
had sales of CDollars 5.3bn (USDollars 4.6bn) last year, has made no secret
of its eagerness to expand its beer business outside Canada.
Labatt's shares rose by 75 cents to CDollars 23.38 yesterday.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>30</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Apple Computer upgrades
Macintosh
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LOUISE KEHOE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SAN FRANCISCO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
APPLE Computer has intro- duced new software for its Macintosh personal
computers with which the company aims to counter competition from
Microsoft's popular Windows program and boost its share of the personal
computer market.
Apple's new System 7 is an enhanced version of the Macintosh operating
system, the program that controls the basic functions of a computer.
The new software 'raises the bar' in what customers will expect from a
personal computer, claimed Mr John Sculley, Apple chairman and chief
executive.
'Macintosh system software is Apple's greatest strength, and we intend to
use this advantage aggressively to become a much bigger player in the
industry,' he said.
'System 7 sets a new standard, thereby widening the gap between what one can
do with a computer, and what one can do with a Macintosh.'
The system includes a new graphical user interface that makes the Macintosh
easier to use, as well as features that enhance the Macintosh's ability to
perform several tasks simultaneously. New Macintosh buyers will get System 7
free with their computers. Most current Macintosh users, however, will have
to upgrade their computers to take advantage of the new software.
System 7 will be offered in the US for Dollars 99. Apple USA also announced
price cuts on the add-on processor and memory boards that will be needed to
upgrade older Macintosh models. The introduction of System 7 demonstrates
that 'Apple is on the offensive,' Mr Sculley claimed.
Many, however, view the software launch as a defensive move aimed at
Microsoft's Windows program which provides IBM-compatible personal computers
with many of the ease-of-use features of the Apple Macintosh.
Apple acknowledged that the introduction of System 7 was delayed for over a
year by technical difficulties.
Although existing Macintosh applications programs will run on System 7,
there are few new programs designed to take full advantage of the new
operating system, analysts noted.
See Technology Page
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>31</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / International Company News: Temporary rescue for French
group
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
VEV, the struggling French textiles group, yesterday agreed to the terms of
a temporary financial lifeboat worked out by the French government with
VEV's bank creditors in a bid to save the company from outright bankruptcy.
The government and banks will together finance VEV's immediate cash needs
for one month - FFr100m (Dollars 17.1m) to FFr250m - while the banks have
agreed to concessions on a portion of their loans to the debt-ridden group.
At the same time, Mr Christian Derveloy, VEV's chairman, is to resign, and
an audit will be undertaken to see if the textiles group can survive.
The government has been anxious to avert the collapse of a group which
employs 11,000 people, many of them in areas of northern France which
already suffer high unemployment. The Interministerial Committee for
Industrial Reconstruction (CIRI), a unit of the Finance Ministry, has
supervised negotiations between VEV and its banks.
An agreement hammered out over the weekend provides for the bank creditors
to abandon an estimated FFr250m of short-term debt and to convert some
FFr500m of medium-term debt into participating loans.
The banks have also been asked to give up their claim on the shares of a
number of VEV's subsidiaries pledged as security for their loans. This
should facilitate the break-up of the group, if this proves necessary, as
most Paris bankers now fear.
VEV has already sold several of its most profitable subsidiaries, such as
Jalla, Pennel &amp; Flipo and Gravograph, in a bid to reduce its debt burden,
which totalled FFr3.3bn at the end of 1989.
Credit Lyonnais, the state-owned bank, is the most heavily exposed creditor,
with loans understood to total more than FFr1.2bn. Other creditors include
Banque Nationale de Paris (BNP), Societe Generale, Credit Commercial de
France (CCF), Credit du Nord and Banque Francaise du Commerce Exterieur
(BFCE).
The banks had earlier flatly refused to accept much broader concessions
proposed by the CIRI.
VEV emerged in 1987 out of the ashes of the Prouvost group, which Mr
Derveloy then managed. Using VEV as his vehicle, Mr Derveloy not only beat
off a stock market assault on Prouvost by the Chargeurs group, but also won
control of the group away from the Prouvost family which had hired him.
Although he succeeded in this battle, Mr Derveloy is generally thought to
have got the worse of a peace deal with Chargeurs signed the following year,
through which he gave up Prouvost's profitable wool trading and carding
operations to Chargeurs, keeping its textiles and clothing divisions.
Mr Regis Bello, formerly chief executive of the A. Dewavrin Fils group, was
expected yesterday to replace Mr Derveloy at the head of the group. Mr
Derveloy was expected to offer to sell his 5.4 per cent VEV stake for a
symbolic FFr1.
VEV's board was due yesterday to finalise 1990's accounts, which are
expected to show a loss of over FFr500m. By yesterday evening, however, the
results had not yet been published.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>32</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK Company News: Business spread behind Power Corp's advance
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KIERAN COOKE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   DUBLIN
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
POWER Corporation, the Dublin-based property development company, has
announced pre-tax profits for 1990 up from IPounds 10.26m to IPounds 15.59m,
or Pounds 14m sterling.
Turnover increased 13.5 per cent to IPounds 35.12m. After tax of IPounds
3.38m (IPounds 2.31m) earnings per share came out at 10.54p, compared with
8.65p. Mr Robin Power, chairman, said that the company had performed
exceptionally well given the difficult market conditions.
'We are the only property company quoted on the UK market to have achieved
results in line with forecasts of 14 months ago. This is due to the spread
of business between Ireland, the UK and the US.'
The company said the value of its property portfolio at the end of 1990
stood at IPounds 352m, up from IPounds 33m when the company came to the
market at the end of 1987. An independent valuation resulted in net assets
per share of 198p at the year end, compared with 207p.
Power has been involved with Brent Walker, the troubled leisure
conglomerate, in the Trocadero site in central London and in the Blackpool
Tower shopping centre.
Mr Power said that the deal with Brent Walker, involving the swapping of
Brent's 50 per cent stakes in the two developments and Power's 50 per cent
stake in the Island site adjacent to the Trocadero, was still subject to
some consents. 'We had expected things to be finalised two weeks ago but
there have been some hold ups.'
He added that the company intended to retain only 50 per cent of the
Trocadero. When the development was completed and an attractive price could
be obtained the 50 per cent from Brent would be disposed of.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>33</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Brent Walker shares drop ahead of loss
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By RICHARD GOURLAY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
BRENT Walker's shares tumbled yesterday as the heavily borrowed leisure
group confirmed that losses last year would lead to a 'major reduction in
shareholders' funds'.
The company has also delayed announcement of its preliminary results from
tomorrow until next Monday. Brent Walker's shares closed 16p lower at 40p.
'Although the group produced profits at the operating level, it sustained a
substantial loss for the year after taking into account interest,
exceptional items and taxation,' the company said. It made a pre-tax profit
of Pounds 82.2m in the year to December 1989.
The delay in the 1990 results pushes back publication of the financial
restructuring plan Brent Walker is thrashing out with Hill Samuel, the
merchant bank acting as its advisers.
The steering committee of creditor banks, led by Standard Chartered, has yet
to see a Touche Ross report on Brent Walker's assets and liabilities on
which the package will be based. The firm was asked last November for the
report when the banks agreed a standstill on Pounds 1.4bn of debt. Banks
expect a write-down in Brent Walker's asset values of Pounds 1bn to about
Pounds 100m net of debt.
London Stock Exchange, Page 40
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>34</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / TVS unveils plan to raise equity as it falls into red
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By RAYMOND SNODDY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
TVS Entertainment, the ITV company for the south of England, yesterday
announced pre-tax losses of Pounds 8.3m and cancelled the final dividend at
the same time as unveiling plans to raise new equity.
The new equity will, however, only become available if TVS retains its
lucrative and hotly-contested southern franchise.
TVS declined to give any details on this before tomorrow's deadline for bids
for new 10-year franchises beginning in 1993.
The financial package will include a new shareholder and promises of further
investment from the company's existing French shareholders, Canal Plus, the
subscription channel and Generale d'Images, the communications company.
TVS would need the capital injection to fulfil its programme obligations
because of the losses sustained in the 1988 acquisition of MTM, the US
production company, in a Dollars 320m (Pounds 189m) deal.
At least three well-funded bidders are going for the TVS franchise - MAI,
the marketing and financial services group, Mr Michael Green's Carlton
Communications and the David Frost/Richard Branson joint venture.
TVS yesterday announced losses arising out of a poor performance from the US
group. TVS made a profit of Pounds 16.8m in the year to end-December,
compared with a profit of Pounds 20.8m in the 14 months to the end of 1989.
However, an exceptional provision of Pounds 20.7m was made against US
programme stock. MTM had four new series cancelled by the US networks last
year - Capital News, FM, City and You Take the Kids. In addition, Pounds
4.4m has been set aside for further redundancies.
An extraordinary charge of Pounds 4m, against an extraordinary gain of
Pounds 30.4m a year earlier, resulted in a net loss of Pounds 10.1m, or
17.6p a share, compared with a net profit of Pounds 40m, or 8.8p per share.
Turnover was Pounds 262.1m (Pounds 325.5m).
Earlier this year, TVS tried to sell MTM, famous for programmes such as Hill
Street Blues and St Elsewhere. Despite much interest, no one would pay more
than Dollars 70m. MTM has been withdrawn from the market.
In Britain, TVS increased its share of ITV advertising revenue to 11.4 per
cent - the highest in its history.
The decision that TVS is 'unable to pay further dividends' means that the
interim payout of 3p in November is the final one.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>35</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Severn Trent to pay Pounds 212m for BET unit
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CLARE PEARSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
SEVERN TRENT, the water company, has agreed to pay Pounds 212m to win Biffa,
one of the UK's leading waste disposal concerns, from BET, the debt-laden
business services group.
The deal means Severn Trent will finally gain a significant presence in
waste management. Last year, Severn Trent decided not to proceed with an
earlier attempt to do so by taking over Caird, a listed company.
BET put Biffa up for sale three months ago, as part of a review of its
funding capabilities and management structure.
Analysts yesterday expected the company's net debt to fall to about Pounds
250m after completion of the sale, which produced proceeds at the top end of
market expectations.
Mr John Bellak, Severn Trent's chairman, said: 'We are delighted to have
been able to buy such a good business at a fair price.'
Mr Nicholas Wills, BET's chairman, said a range of potential acquirers and
joint venture partners had shown interest.
Severn Trent's shares closed 3p down at 277p and BET's were 2p lower at 178p
yesterday.
Biffa, one of the largest presences in the UK waste management business,
made profits before interest of Pounds 17.8m on sales of Pounds 102.3m in
the year to the end of March. No debt is being taken on with Biffa. Mr
Bellak said Severn Trent would be funding it through borrowings incurred by
its public limited company.
The deal intensified speculation about the fate of the 29.9 per cent stake
in Caird with which Severn Trent was left after it dropped its bid last
October, when Caird cut its profit forecast.
Mr Bellak insisted yesterday that all options remained open. Caird's shares
closed unchanged at 75p.
Mr Bellak said that, once Biffa was aligned with the company's existing
business, waste would account for about 15 per cent of total group turnover.
For BET, the sale comes at the end of a turbulent spring which saw a bear
raid on its shares early in February.
A new chief executive, Mr John Clark, took over last month from Mr Wills.
BET has said that it wanted to dispose of Biffa because of the risks arising
from its exposure to environmental legislation.
Mr Martin Bettington stays on as managing director of Biffa, which is best
known for its UK collection and landfill activities.
Using experience acquired in their core water business as a basis for
assuming a wider role in waste management has been a priority for most of
the 10 water companies since they were privatised in November 1989. Severn
Trent's is the biggest step taken in the sector to date.
In February, Wessex Water announced a Pounds 125m joint venture with Waste
Management of the US, one of the world's biggest treatment and disposal
groups.
Lex, Page 20
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>36</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFSFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Drexel details settlement plan
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
DREXEL Burnham Lambert, the US investment bank which filed for Chapter 11
bankruptcy protection 15 months ago, yesterday revealed details of a complex
settlement plan.
Under the agreement, Drexel's estate will be split between creditors and
parties making claims against it under securities law.
The settlement plan comes after judicial pressure to avoid a lengthy,
litigious liquidation.
There are still hurdles but lawyers in the case suggest it could be over by
early 1992, leaving a small 20-person concern to handle Drexel's illiquid
assets.
Under the agreement, the estate - reckoned at more than Dollars 2bn (Pounds
1.15bn) - is divided so that:
Administrative costs of the bankruptcy will be paid first, followed by
Dollars 150m-Dollars 200m of secured claims and a further Dollars 150m
payment into the Securities and Exchange Commission's civil disgorgement
fund;
The next Dollars 1.3bn is split 85:15 between fixed creditors and securities
litigants;
The next Dollars 700m is split 60:40 between the same parties; Thereafter,
the split is 50:50.
About Dollars 300m-Dollars 400m of particularly illiquid assets will go into
a a new entity to be owned by a 'liquidating trust'. This seems likely to be
sold eventually.
Under the plan, all securities litigation against Drexel would cease and
some 200 Drexel employees - though not Mr Fred Joseph, the former chief
executive - would be released from any new litigation claims.
Drexel will also 'pool' its own legal actions with those of the Federal
Deposit Insurance Corporation, which regulates the troubled thrift industry,
and certain securities litigants, in cases where there is a common
defendant. This joint effort could apply in claims against former Drexel
employees, in particular Mr Michael Milken, who headed the lucrative junk
bond operation.
Drexel will get 14 per cent of money collected from such litigation, up to
Dollars 400m.
Perhaps the biggest hurdle is the Internal Revenue Service, which has filed
a Dollars 5.3bn claim and is not included in the settlement plan. Unless a
deal can be struck with the IRS, the merits of this claim will be heard by
the courts next month. If they grant an award above a certain sum -
undisclosed - the settlement agreement could be aborted.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>37</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / US economic hopes rise as output level stabilises
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL PROWSE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
US INDUSTRIAL production stabilised in April after six months of decline,
bolstering hopes that the recession may be bottoming out.
A rise of 0.1 per cent in industrial output, while no more than a tentative
pointer, follows other mildly encouraging statistics, including a slower
rate of decline in employment, an increase in the index of leading
indicators and the start of a housing recovery.
The better figures for April, however, were accompanied by revisions to
previous statistics. The Federal Reserve said production fell 0.6 per cent
in March - twice as much as initially estimated. In the first quarter,
industrial production fell at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 9.6 per
cent.
The tiny increase in output last month does not signal that the US recession
is over but it suggests that the rate of decline has eased significantly.
Most forecasters expect the US economy to hit bottom sometime during the
summer and then to begin a weak recovery.
Last month's improvement was led by car and truck production, which
increased at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 10.8 per cent. This sector
was the biggest depressing influence on the economy in the previous six
months.
Excluding motor vehicles, industrial production fell 0.2 per cent last
month. The weakness was concentrated in non-durable goods, mining and
utilities. Capacity utilisation fell 0.2 points to 78.3 per cent.
The firming of production mostly reflected increases in the output of
durable consumer goods generally, which rose at an annual rate of 3 per
cent. Apart from motor vehicles, sectors sensitive to the cost of money  -
such as furniture, carpeting and home appliances - registered increases.
The industrial production index last month stood at 105.1 compared with 100
in 1987. It was 3.4 per cent below the level of a year ago and about 5 per
cent below the peak hit last September.
Recession hits states, Page 6
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20 Chart (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>38</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Hurd opposes wider role for EC on labour issues
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BUCHAN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
HOPES IN the European Community that Britain might be softening its
opposition to EC labour market legislation were dashed yesterday.
Mr Douglas Hurd, UK foreign secretary, told other EC ministers in Brussels
that he was against proposals to extend majority voting - as opposed to
unanimous voting - to labour and social issues. Majority voting would
prevent Britain, or any member state, from vetoing parts of the social
policy programme and allow the EC a greater say in labour and social issues.
'It would be foolish to commit the community to policies in the social and
employment field which involve potentially enormous costs without regard to
growth,' Mr Hurd said.
Mr Jacques Delors, European Commission president, said: 'I feel like someone
who at the start of this century heard people say that the abolition of
child labour would cause the general collapse of the economy.'
The foreign secretary said Britain had dispelled the cloud of bad industrial
relations that had long hung over it. 'We do not want any pretext for
leading industry back into that situation,' he said.
The UK has been the only opponent of the EC Social Charter but it appeared
to come to terms with some of the legislation, such as written proof of
contracts.
On Monday, Mr Michael Howard, employment secretary, said in an interview
with the Financial Times that Britain now supported most elements of the
social char-ter.
Mr Delors countered Mr Hurd's complaint that social matters would be subject
to over-centralised regulation by saying that the commission was relying
heavily on dialogue between European employers and trade union
organisations.
Other EC ministers re-sponded angrily to Mr Hurd's remarks. Mr Gianni De
Michelis, the Italian foreign minister, warned that Britain could not hope
to get away with vetoing the whole EC political union on social policy
grounds alone.
Mr Mark Eyskens, Belgian foreign minister, suggested that the UK might be
left out of EC social policy-making.
It is unlikely such a compromise would be acceptable to other member states
which might complain that UK industry was escaping the costs of labour
regulation.
The Luxembourg presidency was proposing to extend majority voting to issues
of contractual conditions of employment and management consultation of
workers.
Majority votes now apply only to measures to improve workers' health and
safety, which generally have UK support. Under the Luxembourg plan,
unanimous voting would only be retained for social security issues.
Parliament, Page 11
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20 Photograph Social meeting, Douglas Hurd confers with Dutch
foreign minister Hans van den Broek (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>39</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK consumer credit growth at six-year low
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER NORMAN, Economics Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
BRITISH consumers have been holding back from new borrowing to finance
household goods and other durables although interest rates have fallen and
retail sales rose sharply in March.
The Central Statistical Office reported yesterday that the amounts
outstanding on credit agreements with consumers increased by less in the
first quarter of this year than in any quarter since statistics were first
gathered in the mid-1980s.
The total amount borrowed from finance houses, building societies and on
bank credit cards to purchase consumer goods increased by Pounds 280m to
Pounds 30.03bn in the three months to the end of March. This was the lowest
quarterly increase in this 'narrow' measure of consumer credit business
since records began in 1985. It compares with a quarterly average rise of
Pounds 758m last year.
A broader measure of outstanding consumer credit, which also includes credit
granted in the form of loans by banks on personal accounts and by insurance
companies and retailers, rose by Pounds 840m to Pounds 51.47bn in the same
period. This compares with rises of Pounds 1.03bn and Pounds 1.26bn in the
two previous quarters and is the lowest figure since records began in 1987.
The announcement of the figures, which suggest that recessionary conditions
in the UK are continuing, coincided with the publication of slightly revised
retail sales figures for March, showing a strong volume increase of 3.6 per
cent over February.
The figures show a strong 12.9 per cent surge in the volume of household
goods sales in the month, confirming that the Budget increase in value added
tax to 17.5 per cent from 15 per cent had triggered the retail sales jump.
Household goods are frequently bought on credit but the monthly figures for
narrow credit business showed only a relatively modest increase of Pounds
122m in the amount outstanding in March after increases of Pounds 98m and
Pounds 60m in February and January respectively. Although the March credit
figure was in line with City expectations and had little impact in financial
markets, the difference between the strong growth in retail sales in March
and the subdued appetite of consumers for credit caused some puzzlement
among analysts.
Mr Peter Spencer, UK economist at Shearson Lehman Brothers, said the figures
probably pointed to a recent rise in real incomes as inflation fell.
Consumers had been able to accumulate surplus funds in their bank accounts
and were able to beat the Budget increase in VAT without increasing their
indebtedness, he said.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>40</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Bush pledge on chemical weapons
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER RIDDELL, US Editor
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE US will renounce the use of chemical weapons 'for any reason' and
destroy all its stockpiles within 10 years once international agreement is
reached banning their use, President George Bush said yesterday.
His announcement is intended to give fresh momentum to international talks
which resume today in Geneva on a chemical weapons convention.
The US move goes beyond a draft agreement signed at the US-Soviet summit in
Washington last June to destroy all but 5,000 tonnes each of their chemical
weapons stocks by 2002. In the first eight years after the signing of an
international agreement, this would be reduced to 500 tonnes. For the US,
this would have meant retaining about 2 per cent of its current total.
The White House has been considering the worldwide chemical weapons
initiative as part of a wider series of arms control moves specifically
affecting the Middle East.
In a statement intended to 'demonstrate the US commitment to banning
chemical weapons', Mr Bush said the US was 'formally forswearing the use of
chemical weapons for any reason, including retaliation, against any state,
effective when the convention enters into force and will propose that all
states follow suit'.
He added that the US 'unconditionally commits itself to the destruction of
all our stocks of chemical weapons within 10 years of entry into force of
the convention'.
Previously the US has retained the right to use chemical weapons in
retaliation - and to keep the 5,000-tonne stockpile - until all nations with
such weapons had agreed to eliminate them.
The US originally wished to keep a residual stockpile as a deterrent against
countries such as Iraq which might use chemical weapons in war but
Washington has changed its view, partly as a result of the Gulf war. The US
not only won through the use of conventional weapons but also had to
consider, and reject, the possible use of its own chemical weapons as a
retaliation against any Iraqi chemical attack - although none materialised.
Under the terms of the United Nations ceasefire resolution, Iraq is required
to hand over all its stocks of chemical weapons to a UN commission for
destruction.
At today's Geneva talks, the US is calling for the resolution of all
important issues by the end of this year and a final treaty within 12
months. The US delegation will ask that the negotiating committee of the
Conference on Disarmament stays in continuous session from now on.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>41</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / The Lex Column: Stock lending
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The Bank of England has always encouraged the development of stock lending
in London, arguing that the activity brings valuable extra liquidity and
market confidence. In Thursday's Quarterly Bulletin, the Bank will provide
new evidence for its case. In gilts, for example, daily lending volume has
nearly trebled since Big Bang - to around Pounds 6bn. But the really
fast-growing market involves the lending of international securities, where
there is a problem. If London is to maintain its lead as a centre for the
trading of international securities and related lending and borrowing, a
solution must be found for the tax treatment of overseas lenders. The faster
the Inland Revenue agrees a fair mechanism, the better. Otherwise, London
will have shot itself in the foot - again.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>42</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / The Lex Column: British Airways
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The market is inclined to think British Airways will hold its final dividend
next week - and the market is probably right. BA's balance sheet can stand
the strain; the Pounds 20m saved by halving the payout will be dwarfed by
trading losses in the final quarter; the wrath of shareholders is hardly
worth risking in the not unlikely event that cash flows prove insufficient
to meet the group's ambitious capital spending plans.
If the income question dominates the share price in the short term, though,
the issue thereafter is how far BA can recover from the twin traumas of
recession and the Gulf. The outlook at the moment is hazy, with forward
bookings pointing to a 10 to 15 per cent volume downturn year-on-year over
the crucial summer period. The bigger worry is the sharp drop in revenue
yields as the passenger mix shifts towards cheap-fare travellers. To add to
its woes, BA now faces a serious competitive threat on its transatlantic
routes, with the lower cost Virgin certain to put further pressure on
margins as the US carriers United and American go all out for market share.
BA has probably responded as well as any international airline to the
industry's crisis. In a post-Gulf world, however, the relentless growth of
business travel can no longer be taken for granted; and the regulators have
altered the rules.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>43</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / The Lex Column: UK credit
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Meanwhile, it is likely that something more than hairs are being split in
policy discussions between Westminster and Threadneedle Street. The Bank
remains publicly concerned with metaphysical riddles, such as: When is a
crunch not a crunch? (some hours of the Treasury Committee's time went on
this not long ago); and: What is the underlying underlying rate of inflation
(answers on not less than 10 sides of paper). Ministers are increasingly
worried about votes.
The latest statistics suggest they are right to be anxious. The CBI small
firms survey confirms that there is indeed a credit crunch - if you are too
small to borrow outside the banking system. It is small companies who
complain that credit is sometimes difficult, and always too expensive (1 1/2
per cent a month from one clearer). The Bank of England calls that a fall in
credit demand; the victims call it a squeeze, and all too often a fatal one.
That is no way to treat pillars of their local Conservative Associations.
Yesterday's weak credit growth figures also look forbidding. The brief
beat-the-tax-increase retail boom was financed with astonishingly little
borrowing; at these real interest rates, credit demand is indeed price
sensitive. But officials should take care before they cite this as proof
that 'policies are working'. They are likely to be accused of what a former
chancellor called sado-monetarism. Politically switched-on dealers are
likely to pay less than their usual attention to market signals from the
Bank.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>44</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / The Lex Column: UK markets
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Towards the bottom of the roller-coaster, the ride gets bumpy. If the UK is
indeed reaching the trough of the recession, yesterday's bumps are easy to
understand. The retailing and consumer credit figures, Wall Street, the
outlook for UK interest rates - all have a stomach-jolting feel about them.
More jolts ahead: the last two days of the week will bring grim economic
figures (because they are backward-looking) and the Monmouth by-election
result. The Fed, though, shows every sign of taking the US recession
seriously; if that leads to a further easing after today's meeting, Wall
Street's reaction could help London recover its poise, for a day or so at
least.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>45</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / The Lex Column: Severn Trent places a BET on waste
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
FT-SE Index: 2,486.6 (-37.7)
The problem with BET's Pounds 212m agreed sale of Biffa to Severn Trent is
its timing. BET not only has a chief executive so new he is unready to
elaborate a corporate strategy following the sale; it is also in purdah
ahead of its annual results, so the precise shape of its balance sheet can
only be guessed at.
The most one can say is that BET will now be in much better financial
health: it could scarcely be worse. Assuming net debt of Pounds 240m, its
gearing might be 40 per cent, against 86 per cent. Treating its AMPS
(auction market preferred stock) as debt, gearing has dropped to around 150
per cent.
BET has every reason to be satisfied with an exit multiple of 18, close to
what it always said the assets should fetch. With a guaranteed 9p final
dividend, its shares are already on a prospective yield of 6.7 per cent; add
in the interim payment and the yield is just under 10 per cent. This seems
about right until the group sets out its plans. Only a few weeks ago, after
all, the shares were yielding more than half as much again.
It is Severn Trent's shareholders who might have cause for concern, given
that the price is well above rumoured sighting shots of nearer Pounds 170m
and will probably mean dilution for a couple of years. The diversification
into waste management is sensible enough, but Severn's record is hardly
inspiring - remember Caird. The quality of Biffa's earnings is not so
self-evident that Severn can claim a definite success. Any revaluation of
Biffa's implied Pounds 85m of assets will make interesting reading. If it
finally does buy Caird later this year, Severn will have a national spread
in the management of waste. Shareholders must hope it does not become a
waste of management.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20 Graph (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>46</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Green profits
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOE ROGALY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
A Japanese delegation visited a new steelworks in the north of England. It
was losing money. The visitors made money using the same machinery in Japan.
Asked for advice, they came up with 57 nit-picking suggestions. For example,
the British opened their furnace doors to provide an 18-inch gap through
which to shoot finished rods; for the same process the Japanese opened their
doors only six inches. The saving on heat loss was measurable, and
contributed to the profits earned by the Japanese company.
This story was told by Mr Michael Heseltine, the environment secretary, last
week. His lecture is one of the most effective pieces of sales talk for a
hard-headed environmental policy I have seen from any British minister - and
I do not forget Mrs Margaret Thatcher's stirring words about how all we have
of the earth is a life tenancy, with a full repairing lease. Mr Heseltine
does not preach green virtue. There is a paucity of phrases about saving the
planet. Instead there was a large dose of Heseltiniana ('what we need is . .
. a green renaissance of Britain's economy'), spiced with juicy vistas of
multibillions to be made from clean-ups and the production of greener goods.
'Where there's muck there's brass,' the secretary of state reminded his
audience, quoting an estimate that Pounds 850bn will be spent in the
European Community between now and 2000 on new capital equipment,
environmentally-friendly products and associated services. The British share
would be Pounds 140bn. In his characteristically self-effacing way he has
posted copies of the speech to 1,000 chief executives and asked them to join
a 'green club'.
It is customary to question Mr Heseltine's motives. I do not think that in
this address he was primarily concerned with chasing votes for the
Conservative party. His belief is that public concern for the environment
wanes during a recession, when unemployment and the like seem more pressing.
His speech, with its touches about Europe and partnership with industry,
contains an unspoken element of 'this is what you would have had if I had
been prime minister instead of John Major', but only enough to assuage a
modicum of vanity, nothing threatening or out of line. After all, he joined
forces with his ideological opposite - the industry secretary, Mr Peter
Lilley - to make Mr John Collins, Shell UK's chairman, head of a 23-member
advisory committee on business and the environment.
So let us take Mr Heseltine's words at face value. If they favour
regulation, or the setting of standards, they do so on the basis of the
argument that the country with the highest standards will be the one with
the German cars emit the waste-gas equivalent of Chanel No. 5
most competitive manufacturers. We all know, or should, the story of how the
Germans have made their cars exhaust the waste-gas equivalent of Chanel No.
5, with other car makers having to follow. Consumers, and regulators, demand
it.
This beady-eyed approach is to be found in a new book, Costing The Earth, by
Frances Cairncross, environment editor of The Economist newspaper. Ms
Cairncross provides a checklist of a dozen suggestions for company chairmen,
starting with 'put the most senior person possible in charge of
environmental policy'. Her arguments, which are those of a market economist,
seek at each point to attempt some measure of the costs as well as the
benefits of a particular green policy. Thus she says that it would make
sense for African governments to form an ivory cartel, rather than ban the
trade in tusks. That would eliminate middlemen, drive up prices - and ensure
that the elephant survives to earn future revenue. She refers to botanists
who develop non-timber products to demonstrate that rain forests standing
can be worth more than rain forests destroyed.
Among the many sources quoted is the Yale economist Professor William
Nordhaus, who apparently accepts that the benefits of banning
chlorofluorocarbons, responsible for the hole in the ozone layer may
outweigh the costs. But the goal of stabilising carbon dioxide output in
2000 at 1990 levels is alleged to be more costly to achieve than would be
the benefits of avoiding global warming. Ms Cairncross dutifully records
some of the green challenges to the Nordhaus equation, but implies that even
if his sums are wrong his methodology has to be addressed.
The question is, should it be? 'Ultimately, it is easier to think of
environmental issues in terms of ethics than of discount rates,' she writes.
'Most people feel comfortable with the idea that their descendants ought to
enjoy the same natural inheritance as they have themselves received.' She
manages, nevertheless, to fill 256 pages of recycled paper with merciless
analyses of every green proposition.
I would not, however, accuse her, or Mr Heseltine, of confusion. Just
because you are convinced of the imminence of catastrophe is no reason not
to do a few sums. Both the minister and the author accept the precautionary
principle - that in case the worst predictions are right it pays to do
something now. Both perceive that one practical response to the global
upsurge of green sentiment, which Ms Cairncross chronicles, is to use the
profit motive as the driving force for change. Freer than any minister, Ms
Cairncross can argue forcefully for higher energy prices, even taxes on
energy.
In short the agenda is no longer controlled by the goodly folk who first
brought it to our attention. It is part of everyday discourse, and subject
to its rigours. I believe that when the economy picks up, and perhaps
another discovery takes us a few notches higher up the curve of fear, the
costs of not protecting the future will loom larger, and professor
Nordhaus's flawed equations will have to be re-worked. Meanwhile, watch how
you open those furnace doors.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19 Illustration (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>47</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Letter: Government cover for private export insurance
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   From Mr MALCOLM STEPHENS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Sir, Mr Price rightly points out (Letters, May 9) that some other EC
governments provide export credit insurance cover for the more risky
importing countries though they may do this indirectly through
private-sector companies. This is indeed the set-up which will apply in the
UK following the privatisation of the Insurance Services Group of the Export
Credits Guarantee Department. Mr Lilley - in the remarks to parliament to
which Mr Price refers (May 2) - was making the point that the proposed
changes to ECGD will bring it more into line with arrangements in other EC
countries.
As the minister for trade made clear at the report stage of the Export and
Investment Guarantees Bill, the government, after privatisation of Insurance
Services, will provide 100 per cent reinsurance through the continuing ECGD
for business on a handful of importing countries which are not at present
acceptable to the private reinsurance market. He stressed that the need for
this will be kept under review but, subject to satisfactory financial
performance within ECGD's trading account, it will continue for as long as
the government considered it essential to meet exporters' reasonable needs.
This support is likely to be a relatively minor ECGD facility, applying to
only about Pounds 300m a year of exports - not because of government
reluctance to provide a larger facility, but simply because of the
successful progress in negotiating arrangements with the private reinsurance
market which should ensure that the bulk of Insurance Services risks - both
commercial and political - will be placed in the private market upon
privatisation.
It is, perhaps, in this latter respect that future UK arrangements may
differ from those in some other EC countries. The government's aim has been
to privatise the business of Insurance Services. This would not be achieved
if a large element of that business continued to be reinsured by government,
particularly when it could be placed in the private market. The government
has, therefore, sought to maximise the scope of private market reinsurance
in a way that some other EC governments may not yet have done and which is
not damaging to UK exporters' interests.
It is a difference of degree, rather than principle. The government believes
that this approach is already being reflected in steps being taken in
virtually every other EC country to increase private sector involvement in
the provision of export credit insurance.
Malcolm Stephens,
chief executive,
ECGD,
Export House,
50 Ludgate Hill, EC4
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>48</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Leading Article: A compromise path to Emu
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
AFTER THE informal meeting of European Community finance ministers over the
weekend, plans for the EC's expedition to Economic and Monetary Union are
becoming clearer. Those plans may not be to everyone's liking; indeed, they
are probably to nobody's liking. Nevertheless, they represent a sensible
compromise.
Participants will not be allowed to prevent others from starting out towards
Emu, merely because they are unwilling to depart themselves; nor may they
insist on going in the vanguard, however unfit for that position they might
be; and even though countries may move at different speeds, each will do so
under supervision. The goal will not be reached much before the end of the
decade, while a European Central Bank is unlikely to be constructed before
its attainment. Finally, the move towards Emu may require a new budgetary
deal for the EC.
One point now seems clear. The British will have to change their plans
radically. This is not surprising, because they were absurd. The UK not
merely told the other 11 that it was unwilling to go where they wanted, but
intimated that the UK might veto the others' plans. Meanwhile, Britain
insisted that the others should not set out without it, because this would
leave it in the slower group within a 'two-speed' Europe. Further to enhance
the UK's reputation as a team player, it recommended that they should go
somewhere altogether different, towards the 'hard ecu'.
Poor chances
Since the UK's 'hard ecu' plan involves creating a new monetary institution,
which the Germans abhor, and does not introduce a single currency, which the
French (and others) desire, its political chances are close to zero. The
economic merits of the plan are greater than that, but this matters little.
The plan will have to be abandoned.
It was always inconceivable that the UK would veto a treaty on which the
others were determined, any more than it could prevent others from moving to
Emu. The best it could hope for was a degree of influence upon the pace and
nature of the move towards Emu, while not being forced into it itself.
The likely compromise cannot resolve all of the UK's political problems.
Acceptance of a treaty implies a commitment. Once it exists, the UK will
find itself confronted with a choice between participation, on the one hand,
and consignment to the slow group in a 'two-speed' Europe, on the other. The
treaty will certainly call for increased surveillance of economic policy. It
may imply greater fiscal transfers within the EC as well.
Shared interest
The need for parliament to ratify such a treaty is a recipe for trouble. But
since that trouble will arise within the two big parties as much as between
them, they share an interest in making as little as possible of one of the
most important decisions the country will ever take.
All this assumes that the other 11 can agree on the path to Emu. They can do
so, provided that they accept the terms of the one country that does have a
veto. The Germans will not accept the creation of a European Central Bank
before the new currency is introduced, are most unlikely to tolerate a
central bank not at least as independent as the Bundesbank and will not
consent to participation by countries that have not achieved a high degree
of convergence on the German standard.
These conditions are likely to be accepted (or at least appear to be
accepted). Difficulties would still remain. Convergence of inflation is
desirable, for example, but central control over the fiscal policies of
member states is not. How, then, will the EC deal with the problems created,
not by Greece and Portugal (which are economically insignificant), but by
Italy's huge public debt?
What the path to Emu will not involve is still clearer than what it will,
just as who will not be in the vanguard is more obvious than who will. For
all that, there is progress. The shape of the agreement is emerging. It is
one that will impose discomfort upon many - upon the UK above all, but not
only upon the UK.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>49</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Leading Article: A charter for consumers
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
THE prime minister has set himself the task of completing work on his
citizens' charter this summer. If the charter is to form the centrepiece of
the Conservative election manifesto, he would be wise to review his holiday
plans - for while the aims are admirable, many important questions about the
charter's implementation need to be answered if sceptical consumers are to
be convinced of its merits.
The charter is designed to raise the quality of public services which cannot
immediately be privatised or exposed to competition through contracting out.
Budgetary controls can force service providers to make more efficient use of
limited resources, but there is often little that consumers can do to ensure
that their preferences are satisfied. The citizens' charter - more
appropriately a consumers' charter - would strengthen the consumer's voice
with two innovations to mimic the relationship between buyer and seller in
market transactions.
The first would create a contract between the service provider and the
consumer which specified the services to be provided. Thus BR might make the
commuter a range of promises on matters such as punctuality, cleanliness and
reliability of services. NHS patients could be guaranteed treatment within
time limits which depended on the seriousness of the complaint. Council
tenants would be entitled to repairs within a specified period.
Direct redress
This contract would be enforced by the consumer through the second
innovation: simple and direct channels of redress. So there might be rebates
or discounts when a train was repeatedly cancelled. More radically, a
consumer whose NHS operation was cancelled could be entitled to reasonable
reimbursement for the cost of private treatment (some local authorities
already reimburse tenants for the cost of repairs in such circumstances).
So far, so good, if a challenge to the imagination. But when it comes to the
details of how the charter would operate, substantive proposals are lacking.
For a start, which services will be covered? It is hard to see the charter
having much to say about education, unless it offers to pick up the fees for
Eton for parents let down by their local comprehensive. And what is to stop
managers re-organising services to avoid penalties, simply by sharing the
misery around more equally?
Then there are the cost implications of compensating dissatisfied customers.
Even if redress is only in the form of modest cash payments (as BT now
offers when it fails to keep home appointments), the cost is born by other
customers either in higher charges or worse service. The costs become much
more substantial if they empower the customer to claim back the cost of
private provision when the public service fails. For the NHS to make a
similar offer could lead to a rapid explosion of costs unless the service
targets were so modest as to be empty.
Consumers' interests
Consumer empowerment needs more than just redress systems. The evidence
suggests that only a small minority of consumers ever use such systems - and
those in most need are often least able to do so. The achievement of the
regulators who oversee the newly-privatised utilities suggests a model for
advancing the interests of consumers which could be extended to the public
services, although a public service regulator could not use his private
counterpart's most effective weapon - price restraint - in services which
are free at the point of consumption.
Questions such as these do not present insuperable problems, but finding
answers requires a willingness to confront hard issues. Some public services
are poor because they are badly managed: the citizens' charter could
certainly encourage improvements. Others are underfunded, and a charter
would only expose the low levels of service which have become the norm.
To improve many of Britain's public services requires a combination of
consumer power and extra investment. Charters alone will not guarantee the
improvement in public services which all parties now seem committed to
delivering in the 1990s.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>50</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFEFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Observer: Nobbled
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Southampton fortune-teller Madam Fay is quitting her office after 37 years
because burglars keep stealing her crystal ball.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>51</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Observer: Free wheeling
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
The only certain way of determining the real worth of a company car to
employees - and despite Norman Lamont's best endeavours, they still seem to
be a sight more attractive than a 'go-anywhere' London Underground ticket -
is when the purring little perk is taken away from them.
According to advertising agency Foote Cone &amp; Belding, which has just
de-wheeled its staff, the answer is anywhere between Pounds 3,000 and Pounds
7,000 - the range of pay rises it has handed out by way of compensation.
Other companies seem likely to follow suit, notwithstanding threats from
Customs and Excise to levy VAT on those who, unlike some of their
colleagues, decline the cash option and keep the wheels.
FCB owned a fleet of 80 cars with a balance sheet worth of Pounds 1m and an
annual cost - in terms of servicing, insurance and depreciation  - of Pounds
500,000 and decided enough was enough.
Chris Whitworth, the agency's finance director, says that the costs of
providing the company car simply became prohibitive. He reckons many of
those whose cars were taken away have not even bothered to replace them.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>52</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Observer: Time out
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
One thing unlikely to change after the weekend elections in Nepal, land of
timeless beauty, is the time.
The Himalayan kingdom is thought to be the only country in the world which
lives in its own, 15-minute time warp. Since 1985, it has set its clocks
four hours and 45 minutes ahead of GMT - a quarter of an hour in advance of
neighbouring India.
Such demonstrations of independence carry great weight in a country trapped
between the giants of India and China. But some Nepalis insist the
difference is strictly scientific.
Time is determined by the longitude of the centre of a country, which in
India was set during the Raj at 82.5 degrees. That longitude goes nowhere
near Nepal, let alone cuts it in half, according to Gopal Sharma, chief
reporter at the country's government-owned newspaper, The Rising Nepal.
Religion, it seems, also plays a part in setting the clocks. The longitude,
which actually divides Nepal and provides the reference point for local
time, cuts through a mountain called Gauri Shanker named after the wife of
Lord Shiva, the Hindu god of destruction and rebirth.
If the Congress party, the centrist group backed by India, emerges
victorious, there could be pressure to realign Nepalese time. But as Shiva
can bestow power upon those who please him, any sensible politician with an
ounce of ambition
may be best advised to leave well alone.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>53</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Observer: Idle Hans
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Let us not be beastly to the Germans, but are they really the dedicated,
horny-handed toilers they are made out to be? According to the German
Economic Institute, they seem increasingly ready to bunk off work and head
for the nearest beer hall.
The institute reckons those employed in industry should be clocking up an
average of just over 1,650 hours a year. But they are typically falling 145
hours short - for the most part, strange though it may seem, on Mondays and
Fridays.
By comparison the British, no longer the sick men and women of Europe, are
expected to put in more than 1,750 hours - and record a 'no show' for only
119 of same.
Both, however, look lazy alongside the Japanese who on average should be in
the factory for more than 2,200 hours each year, and bow out for a mere 36
hours.
The dedication of the Japanese could be something to do with the widespread
belief that while you can be sick, it must be in your own time and at your
own expense. The absence of the Germans, it appears, could be put down to
the generous compensation available and to competition among doctors to hang
on to patients by never knowingly refusing a sick note.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>54</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAFAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Observer: Off the record
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
It is hardly surprising that by the time Sir Bernard Ingham left 10 Downing
Street, Maggie's craggy mouthpiece was not on good terms with Sir Geoffrey
Howe, who helped to jemmy the iron lady out of power. The surprising thing
is that relations between the two men did not suffer a good while earlier,
given an incident in 1981.
Oddly enough, it is not recalled in the much publicised memoirs in which
Ingham, bulky and indispensable like the great lady's handbag, has given a
compelling if not entirely unbiased account of his days and nights in Number
10. Puffed-up media lobby correspondents with mischievous motives, and
ministers who wilfully spoke out of turn come in for considerable stick.
What happened in 1981 was that Ingham himself quickly learned, at both his
and Sir Geoffrey's expense, about the danger of making unguarded, albeit
unattributable, remarks to the 'reptiles' - to borrow Denis Thatcher's
epithet - of the parliamentary lobby.
With Britain struggling to escape recession, Ingham found himself late at
night in a Copenhagen hotel room with assorted lobby reporters topping up
tumblers and bemoaning a boring EC summit meeting bogged down by quotas on
Japanese car and video-recorder imports.
Surely, they goaded the chief press secretary, Margaret Thatcher's free
market philosophy could not embrace artificial restraints on trading? Ingham
agreed, conceding that the only reason such measures were necessary at the
time was to protect a British economy in a 'bloody awful' state.
The tabloids sobered up and splashed their front pages with the quotation,
attributed to a 'top Thatcher aide'. As if that would not have been bad
enough in itself, Sir Geoffrey who was then chancellor had just stretched
the nation's credibility by pronouncing 'we have come to the end of the
recession'.
Howe was highly unamused; Ingham a little bit wiser.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>55</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Uphill fight in the high street / Chart the continuing
struggle of Britain's consumer services sector as it fights to survive
recession
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALICE RAWSTHORN and JOHN THORNHILL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
South Molton Street's designer clothes stores shut up shop for a few hours
yesterday in a protest against a proposed rent rise.
The threatened rent rise looked the last straw for the stores on one of
London's most fashionable shopping streets. Like other retailers, travel
companies and leisure groups that make up the consumer service sector, they
are struggling against the worst recession most of them have known.
Several companies have gone bust. The collapse of International Leisure
Group (ILG) and Lewis's department stores alone cost nearly 4,000 jobs.
Other companies can only hope that they can cling on until the autumn when
economists expect the outlook to be brighter.
Why has this sector, once seen as the key to Britain's economic resurgence,
suffered so severely in this recession? Are its difficulties purely a
product of short-term economic pressure, or are they related to longer-term
changes in consumer markets? And what will the sector look like after the
recession?
Consumer services were relatively resilient in the last recession of
1980-81. This was because real interest rates were comparatively low - in
that base rates were lower than inflation - and companies had been run
cautiously after the oil shocks of the mid-1970s. There was relatively
little expansion in leisure, entertainment and even in retailing. Video
shops, theme parks, superstores and multiplex cinemas were all in their
infancy in the early 1980s.
This recession is different. Real interest rates are high and the consumer
sector is far larger. The latest unemployment figures show that employment
in the service sector (which includes commercial as well as consumer
services) fell by 82,000 to 15.76m in the final quarter of 1990. Marks and
Spencer, which is today expected to disclose static profits, recently
announced 850 redundancies.
Moreover, many consumer service companies are burdened by high borrowings
after a decade of expansion. When interest rates rose and consumer spending
declined, companies such as ILG and Lewis's could no longer afford to pay
the interest on their debt. Brent Walker, the troubled leisure group which
owns William Hill betting shops and Brighton Marina, is still struggling to
restructure the Pounds 1.4bn debt amassed in its acquisitions of the 1980s.
Certain areas of consumer services have emerged unscathed. This is mainly
because some groups of consumers are better off thanks to high interest
rates, notably the over-50s, with low mortgages and high savings, and the
under-25s, who have few financial commitments.
The companies that service these particular customers are still faring well.
Blackpool Pleasure Beach is busy, partly thanks to its popularity with the
over-50s. The beach has invested heavily in new attractions for them, such
as the afternoon karaoke 'sing-alongs' in the Cabaret Rooms. So far this
season, despite rain and recession, attendance levels are 14 per cent higher
than last year.
The cinema is flourishing too, partly because of its appeal for the
under-25s. Cinemas enjoyed their best year for a decade in 1990 with average
weekly admissions of 1.88m people. So far this year, they have fared even
better with average admissions of 1.94m a week in the first quarter.
But pleasure beaches and cinemas are the exceptions. The worst-affected
companies are those catering for the 25 to 40-year-olds, the 'yuppies' of
the 1980s, many of whom bought property near the peak of the housing market
and are now saddled with hefty mortgage repayments and credit card debt.
The 'designer' shopping centres that opened in the 1980s, such as Tobacco
Dock in east London, are littered with boarded-up windows. Restaurants are
suffering too. Mr Alistair Little, who runs the eponymous restaurant in
London's Soho, first noticed the slowdown towards the end of last year. His
regulars have since been eating out less often and spending less on their
meals.
Companies linked to the housing market have also suffered. Home furniture,
one of the first areas to be affected, saw sales fall by 6 per cent in real
terms to Pounds 4.7bn last year. This was devastating for Lowndes Queensway,
one of the biggest furniture retailers which had just completed a Pounds
450m leveraged buy-out. Last summer, Lowndes called in the receiver.
In general, the recession has accentuated the difference between the
stronger and weaker players. In the pubs market, Mr Peter Jarvis, chief
executive of Whitbread, one of the biggest brewers, has noted the difference
between 'good pubs in large premises with decent facilities' which are still
doing well and the 'bad pubs in run-down areas' which are 'finding life very
difficult'.
When the end of the recession comes into sight later this year, the critical
question for the consumer service sector is what its long-term consequences
will be.
Some areas of consumer services are unlikely to return to their
pre-recession buoyancy. The designer shops and expensive restaurants in the
'yuppie' market would probably have contracted even without the economic
downturn. The self-indulgent young adults of the 1980s are now settling into
the responsibilities of family life as they enter their 30s.
Other areas will return to growth once the economy recovers. In furniture
retailing, where rationalisation has been severe - the number of stores has
fallen by 600 to about 14,000 in the past five years - there is sure to be
scope for re-investment.
The established companies, such as Magnet and MFI, are so burdened by debt
that new investors may move into the market. Argos, the catalogue retailer,
has been studying furniture retailing for several years and now plans to
open four stores. Ikea, the Swedish group which already owns three UK
furniture stores, plans to accelerate its expansion by opening up to 15
stores by the mid-1990s.
In other markets such as pubs, where rationalisation has been less intense,
the recession has tended to accelerate existing trends. The brewers have
speeded up the process of closing down their smaller, scruffier pubs in
favour of concentrating investment on more promising premises. Whitbread
shut 350 of its 6,650 pubs last year and spent Pounds 250m on new pubs and
restaurants such as Wayside Inns, its upmarket traditional country pubs.
But all consumer service companies face the challenge of getting to grips
with the long-term changes in the marketplace.
One important issue is the change in demographics: the decline in the number
of teenagers and the corresponding growth of the elderly population. This
poses obvious problems for businesses like fashion shops and theme parks
that depend on the teenage market.
Burton, which owns the Top Shop teenage fashion chain, is in the middle of a
strategic review of all its operations. Sears, which owns Miss Selfridge and
Dolcis, is reshuffling its retail portfolio. The focus of its investment is
now on 'family' concepts such as Adams children's wear shops and the Olympus
sports chain.
Alton Towers, the Staffordshire theme park owned by Pearson (which owns the
Financial Times), is concentrating its investment on enhancing its appeal to
families. In the past, it has relied on 'white knuckle' rides to attract the
thrill-seeking under-25s (who represented two-thirds of its 2m visitors last
year). It is now spending Pounds 6m on two new family rides - the Haunted
House and Runaway Mine Train - in the hope of attracting more family groups
to lessen the blow of the shrinking teenage market.
Demographic changes will also intensify the financial pressure on the
sector, notably on retailers and fast food chains, which have traditionally
depended on a regular influx of teenage employees on low wages.
These companies are already examining alternatives. McDonald's, the fast
food group, is developing a programme for part-time managers so some
employees, notably women with children, can return to work after career
breaks. It is also recruiting older managers who have spent most of their
careers in other industries.
The shortage of teenage recruits will almost certainly force companies to
offer higher pay, thereby increasing overheads at a time when they already
face rising property costs due to rent and rate reviews, like those on South
Molton Street.
Demographic and financial pressures aside, the chief challenge for the
service sector is to respond to the continuing demand from consumers for
higher quality in terms of products and service. This was one of the main
trends of the 1980s and has continued, despite the recession, as the pattern
of trading in pubs suggests.
In some markets, the drive towards higher quality means the successful
companies will be those that continually invest in improving their products.
The brewers will carry on upgrading their pubs. A recent study by the
Brewer's Society suggested that as many as 8,000 of Britain's 80,000 pubs
will close over the next decade so the brewers can concentrate resources on
their larger, more modern pubs.
Similarly, food retailers will continue the process of closing their old
supermarkets to concentrate investment on new superstores, the giant stores
selling everything from avocados to ankle socks.
M and S, which already runs eight edge-of-town clothing and food stores,
plans to open up to 25 over the next few years. Tesco has identified 200
prospective sites, many of which will be superstores. However, Sir Ian
MacLaurin, Tesco's chairman, said it also plans to stay in the high street
by developing 'high-quality neighbourhood stores'.
In other markets, the quality trend could create opportunities for
expansion. These will be the less 'mature' markets, such as restaurants and
hotels, that have been constrained by the comparatively unsophisticated
taste of British consumers. The British undoubtedly became more cosmopolitan
during the 1980s but most Britons have never tasted pizza and still stay at
home for their holidays.
This means that companies like Forte, the hotel group, can expect to expand
by 'converting' new consumers, in its case the people who do not usually
stay in hotels. One of Forte's most successful concepts is the five year-old
Travelodge budget chain.
Travelodge, which offers a standard package of a double room for the fixed
price of Pounds 29.95, is designed for the leisure travellers who cannot
afford luxury hotels but are wary of the poor facilities in bed and
breakfasts. There are now 81 Travelodges. Forte plans to open 40 a year at
least until 1995.
Forte may be right and the British will have become converts to hotel
holidays - and pizza eating - by the end of the 1990s. But in the meantime,
Forte, South Molton Street and the rest of the consumer service sector face
at least another six months of financial pressure as they wait for the end
of the recession.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18 Graph (Omitted). Graph (Omitted). Graph (Omitted).
Illustration (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>56</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Arts: Machinery of war / Review of exhibitions in London
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MARY ROSE BEAUMONT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
'My subject is War, and the pit of War' wrote Wilfred Owen in 1918, just
before he was killed. David Smith's 'Medals for Dishonor' are about anger,
as well as pity, anger against warmongers and the exploiters of the
defenceless. Smith is best known in this country as a welder of large
abstract sculptures in stainless steel. The Tate Gallery owns a fine 'Cubi'
of 1964, now augmented, thanks to a generous loan by his daughters of two
earlier, more figurative sculptures. Again, thanks to the family, we can now
see the extraordinary series of fifteen bronze reliefs which he made between
1937 and 1940 at the Imperial War Museum, brilliantly displayed in glass
cabinets.
Unlike his contemporary American abstract expressionists, Smith travelled
widely in Europe in 1935-36, ending up in Britain. He was a violent opponent
of rising Fascism in Germany and Italy, and his awareness of the Spanish
Civil War was strengthened by seeing Picasso's 'Guernica' when it was
exhibited in New York. The specific impetus for the Medals was a visit to
the British Museum in May, 1936, where he saw a display of First World War
medals by German and French artists. He was especially drawn to the savage
propaganda of the German medals, which he related to the disintegrating
political situation in America.
Smith's targets were politicians, diplomats, the press (in particular,
William Randolph Hearst), the clergy and what he called 'War Exempt Sons of
the Rich,' whose medallion has a Greek inscription translating as 'soft
cookies' across the centre. The imagery is strongly influenced by European
Surrealism, especially Dali, and he borrows Picasso's symbolic use of the
bull to represent the 'disemboweller of the lie of Franco.' Smith also
quotes from Goya's 'Disasters of War' and draws on the apocalyptic language
of paintings by Bosch and Breughel. The medallions were made with extreme
difficulty, using dentists' and jewellers' tools on hard dental stone.
Smith's anger seems quite literally to bubble through the surface. The first
(and only, as it turned out) edition was cast in bronze and exhibited in
1940 to a distinct lack of acclaim. Since none was sold, they have remained
in the family and are now exhibited with related drawings. Taken together,
the ferocious anti-war and anti-corruption statements which they make are as
relevant today as they were then. (Until June 23).
*****
Denis Masi is also concerned with the machinery of conflict, with man's
never-ending desire for territorial expansion at the expense of the weak,
with paraphernalia of domination which includes imprisonment and
surveillance. Masi's concepts are based on issues and polemics, which until
recently have been more appropriately displayed as installations in public
places. With the new wall work, Masi has come off the street and into two
galleries, Edward Totah and Anderson O'Day. Although he has moved away from
installations, the work has lost none of its impact. Elegant and beautifully
crafted, Masi's wall pieces lie in wait, crouched by sleek feline creatures,
waiting to pounce on the imagination.
The smoothly finished weld mesh and copper cladding of 'Border No. 3' does
not conceal that it is about territory, both physical and psychological,
whether it be Northern Ireland, Kuwait or Kurdistan. The searchlight,
described as a found object, in 'Make It Known,' speaks volumes to the
collective memory of watchtowers at Buchenwald or Long Kesh. Many of the
pieces include a mirror, which gives the viewer back his own image and,
inserted into oxydised copper, as a narrow, horizontal strip behind a weld
mesh cage, must also be understood as an observation device. Either way, the
viewer is drawn into complicity with the artist. 'Territorial Imperative,'
incorporates corrugated steel, a flue and louvers. Uneasily, we wonder
whether we are in a mortuary or a hospital, the flue perhaps an escape route
for smoke from a crematorium. (Until May 25.)
Far removed from politics and the sturm und drang of warring nations are
Lucy Jones's rapturous paintings of her native city at the Flowers East
gallery. Born and bred in London, she celebrates its buildings and monuments
in dazzling colours. Not since Derain, in imitation of Monet, was sent here
by his dealer in 1905 has London been recorded with such panache. Like Monet
and Derain, Jones is magnetised by the river. Drawn to it repeatedly, she
paints it in a variety of moods and colours; the dolphins on the lamp-posts
along the embankment take on a vigorous life of their own, here green and
red, there purple and brown.
Buses and cars lollop round Trafalgar Square like Dinky toys or hurtle
towards Big Ben and the Houses of Parliament. Jones's rainbow-hued London is
the city of her mind, bearing little relation to the archetypal grey, wet
Saturday afternoon. Her self-portraits are a new avenue down which she has
raced full tilt, revelling in the permutations of colour contrast: Van Gogh
sunflower yellow is the background for the violet-clad artist in the
full-length portrait, 'All of Lucy Jones.' (To May 26.)
*****
Laura Ford's paintings and sculptures at Benjamin Rhodes Gallery have a
superficial look of innocence, which proves to be entirely false. Little
girls, dressed in neat embroidered pinafores, stand atop full mountains of
foam cushions. Their childish appearance is subverted by a menacing pair of
pistols, whilst in place of a head there is a tangled mass of Gorgon locks
or a bursting flower. Surrealism is disturbingly mixed up with nursery rhyme
illustration, more Struwelpeter than Kate Greenaway. Far from being a Teddy
Bears' Picnic, the painting 'Shagpile' looks more like a gang-bang or ritual
slaughter. Ford's declared liking for the sinister cautionary tales of
Patricia Highsmith is made visible in her frightening and unpleasant
subtext. (To June 8.)
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17 Photograph 'Propaganda for 1939-40' by David Smith (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>57</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Arts: Same Old Moon - Globe Theatre
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
  By MALCOLM RUTHERFORD
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
After having seen the first part of Same Old Moon at the re-opening of the
Oxford Playhouse last month, one went to its arrival in London with the
heart somewhere between the knees and the boots. Yet it is amazing what hard
work and a better stage can bring. This is not another Dancing at Lughnasa,
and not only because Geraldine Aron does not write as well as Brian Friel -
it would be hard to do that. Ms Aron's piece also lacks the imagination and
the ability to create a world on its own that are so conspicuous in Dancing.
But, seen at the Globe, it is not a bad play.
The Oxford theatre is cramped and box-like, perhaps fatally so. The Globe
has space enough to illustrate the title. The moon shines on Dublin, Galway,
London and such faraway places as Rhodesia (as Zimbabwe then was) and
Australia. The question is whether it is always the same moon. One answer is
given by the Irish barman who turns on the wireless and hears of the
Japanese attack on Pearl Harbour. 'Always the same old news,' he says in
disgust as he turns it off. In other words, it depends on the way you look
at it.
Brenda, now beautifully played by Gabrielle Reidy with a confidence that the
same actress did not have in Oxford, is catholic, Irish, and wants to get
away and write. She has a father who appears to dislike her. Almost on his
deathbed he confesses it is because they are too similar. He admires her,
however, because unlike him she does not think that it is always the same
old moon. She goes off and does things.
The play has some strong vignettes. A nun demonstrates to Brenda the act of
procreation with a phallus-shaped biscuit and a doughnut. Brenda exchanges
one of her first kisses in return for a ride on a bicycle: it is the bicycle
that gets bent and broken. Best of all is the letter from the Vatican in
response to Brenda's appeal to the Pope. It is signed by Monsignor Flaherty
who adds in brackets 'formerly Martin Flaherty' of a road in Galway.
There are also some cliches: too many attempted jokes about sex and
catholicism. It is not particularly funny that Brenda's father (played by
James Ellis and looking curiously like Sir Bernard Ingham) should adopt all
the prejudices of an Alf Garnett when he arrives in London, complaining
about Pakistanis running the hospital and Jews running the country. A
longish sequence which is devoted to what happens to women when they start
wearing a dressing gown must have been played at least a dozen times before,
though I suppose it has a twist at the end: it is the fear of the same old
dressing gown that spurs Brenda on again.
For my taste it is too Irish, sentimental and maudlin, but others may well
like it and Jenny Killick's direction has improved beyond measure since
Oxford.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17 Photograph Gabrielle Reidy (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>58</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Arts: The Black Rider - Berlin Theatre Festival
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JACKIE WULLSCHLAGER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
To kill your wife in a shooting accident is one thing; to turn the episode
into a musical would seem, gall aside, to invite theatrical fiasco in the
worst of taste. Add lyrics that slide between German and English, a set that
crosses von Sternberg with a western, rock music with fairground honky-tonk,
and disaster looks assured.
So it is with reluctant but moonstruck admiration that I report The Black
Rider (text: William Burroughs) as the star of the Berlin Theatre Festival
(to May 20) and one of the most delightful, inventive, profound and
originally musical musicals composed; a fitting - self-consciously so -
successor to those other mythical English-German concoctions, The Threepenny
Opera and Cabaret.
The Black Rider overlays the modern legend of Burroughs, the Beatnik junkie
who shot his wife, with the old tale of the village clerk who has to pass
muster as marksman before he can marry the gamekeeper's daughter. He makes a
pact in 'silver bullets' with the devil but on his wedding day Satan betrays
him and he shoots dead not the targetted white dove but his wife. This was
the story, converted to a happy ending, of Weber's Der Freischutz. Now
Burroughs, the Texan director and stage designer Robert Wilson, and rock
composer Tom Waits, have reworked the original into a contemporary version.
Other myths get woven in. Wilson's devil is a sleek Master of ceremonies in
whiplash tails who croons the Cabaret welcome 'So come on in/it ain't no
sin/take off your skin/and dance around in your bones'. He introduces the
cast, his 'devil's band', as they step one by one out of a black felt
sentry-box.
For three hours of graceful, cold artifice, they look, act and sound like
figures from the silent movies: movements abrupt, irregular, too fast, too
slow, as if wound up by a shaky hand projector; chalk-white, bony faces,
blackened eye sockets, lips thickened into permanent red pouts. Every image
is ice-hard: hair pulled back crisp or standing up in spikes, clothes
exaggerating bodies with jagged collars, razor pleats, square and
rectangular dresses.
The set continues the theme; Wilson turns children's drawings into
three-dimensional monstrosities. Crooked chairs, two metres high, dangle at
odd angles along with a huge frame whose broken glass juts into the flesh of
its 'living' picture, the gamekeeper's ancestor (Heinz Fossbrink). Pine
trees are scissor cut-outs which collapse and grow again like cartoons,
illuminated sugar pink and lime green against a black forest. Large or small
scale, Wilson is a master of spectacle: the clerk William and his Katchen
floating above the stage for a duet as the great neon sign of a gun descends
before them; the white stockinged leg in red stiletto that appears out of a
slit in the black sentrybox, image of naivety, severity, brittle romance.
Best of all, the whole, the sustained dramatic unity of the vision, is
greater than the sum of its parts. Tom Waits' sarcastic ballads, full of
folk and blues and rock, call back the scarred idealism and mock simplicity
of Kurt Weill, while Burroughs' monosyllabic banality has here found the
setting which makes it seem perfect.
Nursery rhyme humour marries English with German, while Hollywood kitsch
rolls into Teutonic romanticism. Wilson's cast bop and strut and beat out
the mesmeric rhythms in husky tempting voices. The devil (Dominique Horwitz)
has the best tunes, and mocks us for loving them. In 'Last Rose of Summer'
he picks a flower from the floor, affects a tear, disappears into his box
and, inside it, hovers up to the roof of the stage.
Annette Paulmann and Stefan Kurt, as Katchen and William, screech like
vultures and sing like angels. She plays an imaginary piano and draws
patterns in the air as she sings the breathless lyric 'I'll shoot the moon
right out of the sky for you, baby'; he dances a ballet of despair, shock
and loss breaking through his wax face, before rallying with 'I'll be back
on some lucky day'. This production returns to Hamburg's Thalia Theatre
after Berlin, with a stop in Amsterdam on May 14-16. So far plans for a
London visit have not materialised, but this is a show worth a plane ticket.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>59</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Technology: The icon gathers a loyal following - As
Microsoft's Windows 3.0 approaches its first birthday, Della Bradshaw
reflects on the software program that took the computer world by storm
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DELLA BRADSHAW
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Until a year ago, London-based chartered accountants Touche Ross had just
two choices when it wanted to computerise the process of auditing its 1,500
clients.
First Touche could write its own software from scratch - or employ a
contractor to do it - which could prove costly and time-consuming.
Alternatively, Touche could buy a standard software package and try to
adjust the way the firm operated in order to make the auditors' practices
fit the format of the software.
Neither option proved attractive: there was a dearth of readily available
audit support software and the firm was cautious about embarking on a big
software applications drive. Because the bulk of audits are carried out
between November and April - for companies which report their year-ends in
December or March - Touche had to be sure that the software could be
implemented in the slack summer period.
'If we missed that window we were another year away,' relates Mark Stephens,
partner for information technology at Touche. 'Something that took 13 months
to develop was really a two-year programme for us.'
Advised of its imminent arrival, Stephens decided instead to wait for the
Windows 3.0 software program, launched a year ago this month by Microsoft,
the leading US personal computer software company.
The initial success of Windows 3.0 - nearly 3m copies of the program have
been sold worldwide - has been generated because it radically alters how
IBM-compatible personal computers can be used, giving them the look and feel
of an Apple Macintosh.
But more sophisticated users of Windows 3.0, such as Touche, believe its
long-term popularity will be rooted in the ability it gives software
developers to customise their own packages more quickly. 'It takes a third
to a quarter of the time to produce sophisticated software than before,'
says Stephens.
Windows 3.0 is a 'graphical user interface', a program that generates menu
bars, icons and overlapping windows, which can be used with various
applications programs such as word processing or spreadsheets. The interface
enables users to point at symbols and click an electronic 'mouse' to select
functions, instead of typing commands on a keyboard.
What makes Windows 3.0 useful to software developers is that it provides a
'programming environment' which sits on top of the applications package and
enables the procedures within the standard package to be adapted to the
needs of the user organisation. Certain procedures can be ordered in a
different way or eliminated if they are irrelevant.
'In the past we developed word processing packages on the basis of what we
thought users wanted, but you couldn't change them to fit in with the work
pattern that you had in the office,' says David Smith, systems marketing
manager for Microsoft. 'In trying to be general, and develop a package for
every single user in the world, you had to compromise along the way.'
Stephens and his team decided to use Microsoft's Word word-processing
package running under Windows 3.0 as the basis for their development
programme. 'Auditing is a lot about writing but I didn't want to develop a
new word processor. However we couldn't use a standard word processing
package - we needed to tailor it to our specific application,' recalls
Stephens.
So they adapted the Word software, using Windows, to make it look like an
auditing tool. 'From an underlying software standpoint about 95 per cent of
the software is Microsoft. We've done about 5 per cent,' says Stephens. But
he reports that from a user point of view about 80 per cent of software
appears to be a specifically designed for auditing.
The Touche software developers have achieved this by taking all the
word-processing features available in the Word package and linking them
differently. On top of that they have created headings and formats
specifically for their auditors' needs. The progression on standard forms
and layout, for example, mirrors the procedures an auditor would follow in
the course of his job - whether auditing banks or grocery stores.
Although the first software package, launched on 600 machines in August
1990, concentrated on the presentation of the software, this summer
Stephens's department will be adding to the basic features and contributing
to the content of the application. One thing the development team will be
looking at is making the existing software easy to translate - Touche's
Paris office has already shown an interest in going down the same
development route.
Because the development cycles are so short, Touche has even been able to
create several prototype applications and, once appropriate software has
been selected, the rest have been thrown away.
Stephens points out that in spite of the moves towards these programmable
applications packages, the basic applications tools are not completely
ready. Of the five common applications that can be used by most
organisations - word processing, spreadsheet, database, communications and
graphics - Microsoft has developed only two to run under Windows 3.0 -
Excel, the spreadsheet package, and Word. It has also adapted Project, for
project management.
But the success of Windows has persuaded all the large applications software
houses to adapt their most popular packages which run under Dos - the widely
used PC operating system - so that they can take full advantage of Windows.
Lotus, for example, is in the final stages of developing a version of its
popular 1-2-3 spreadsheet package which will fully exploit Windows 3.0, and
is planning to have business graphics for the operating program later this
year, says Robert Ingram, spreadsheet sales and marketing manager for the
company. Borland International has three programming tools which work with
Windows 3.0, and is also adapting its Paradox relational database package
and its Quattro Pro spreadsheet program.
Microsoft estimates that there are now more than 700 software developers
writing new Windows-based applications, all hoping to take a bite of an
ever-growing cherry. The Software Publishers Association in the US estimates
that worldwide sales of Windows 3.0 applications are now second only to
those of Dos applications packages. Market research consultant Dataquest
underlines this optimism: it estimates that by 1992 systems sales of Windows
will have overtaken those of Dos.
The growth in the number of packages to run with Windows 3.0 has changed the
buying patterns of Windows users, says Smith. 'For the first six or seven
months there was an enormous growth in the sales of Windows operating
software. But for the last five months we have seen applications sales shoot
up - sales have quadrupled. Now 85 per cent of Windows users have a Windows
application,' he says.
Initially Windows 3.0 customers were running their existing Dos programs
with the operating system - giving them the advantage of the icon-type
presentation but without the power to move in and out of the applications
provided by Windows 3.0. With Dos programs the user is forced to follow a
series of commands in order to move through the program - like boring a
hole, which you have to climb back out of before you can begin boring
another hole.
The Windows icons enable users to jump between different applications. So
one advantage of combining a Windows application with the Windows 3.0
program, says Smith, is that the user can take text, graphics or numbers
from one applications package and transfer them into another - figures from
a spreadsheet program can be copied into a report being prepared in a word
processing package, say.
Perhaps the biggest advantage is that the two application packages need not
even be provided by the same software companies.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12 Graph (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>60</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: Delors overture fails to unite
Conservatives - European Union
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By RALPH ATKINS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
EUROPEAN Commission suggestions for compromise on economic and monetary
union showed little sign yesterday of uniting the Conservatives on Europe -
or of tapping undiscovered goodwill among Tory MPs to Mr Jacques Delors, the
commission's president.
Suggestions at the weekend that Britain be allowed to sign a treaty without
agreeing on the final goals did nothing to alter the well-rehearsed
convictions of Tories at Westminster.
The anti-federalists, with the Bruges Group in the vanguard, remained
opposed to any deal by which Britain would accept, even tacitly, a single
currency. The most 'pro-Europe' Tories were anxious for Britain to react
positively.
Those in the middle remained sceptical of Mr Delors' vision for Europe and
anxious to avoid being 'bounced' into a treaty the UK might regret. Not even
an opportunity to defer awkward decisions beyond the election swayed
firmly-entrenched views. Words of encouragement were qualified by warnings
that the small print had to be examined carefully.
The government's reaction was also cautious. If a decision was to be
deferred for a future parliament, all options had to be kept open. The 'hard
Ecu' remained on the table. But officials admitted the European Commission
had at least show 'an appreciation of the UK's concerns'.
For some MPs who strongly opposed a single European currency, Mr Delors'
suggestion was acceptable only if it was clear Britain was defering the
decision on whether to accept such a move - not just the timing. And there
was no deadline for a decision.
One right-wing minister said: 'If we can dither indefinitely, it's fine. If
there is a cut-off point to the dithering, it's a fraud,'
Mr Patrick Robertson, secretary of the Bruges Group, said: 'Any compromise
which makes Britain accept a single European currency in principle would be
completely unacceptable. At present there is not enough information anywhere
to be clear exactly what the form of words would be.'
Mr Teddy Taylor, secretary of the European Reform Group, went as far as
saying: 'If the government could negotiate an arrangement 'without
commitment' we feel that this would be a very major advance in the battle to
preserve our freedom and to safeguard the nation against socialist control
and bureaucracy.'
But Mr William Cash, the prominent anti-Federal Europe MP for Stafford, said
it was 'unrealistic' to expect what amounted to a two-tier Europe to work in
practice.
Among the middle ground of the party, there was anxiety, to be seen as
pro-European, like Mr John Major. But there was suspicion about Mr Delors'
blueprint for Emu. Mr Terence Higgins, chairman of the Commons' Treasury
select committee, said Mr Delors, 'thinks he is losing the argument' and so
was trying to get British agreement for allowing other EC members to proceed
on a pre-determined timetable.
For most on the pro-European wing, however, the plan was another opportunity
the UK appeared set to rebuff. Mr Hugh Dykes, MP for Harrow East, said: 'How
crazy it is that even when the commission president proposes a helpful
compromise, meeting specific British hesitations, it is denounced by a small
number of hysterical anti-marketeers.'
Editorial comment, Page 18
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>61</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: UN contribution
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
BRITAIN will contribute Pounds 15m to the United Nations Population Fund and
the International Planned Parenthood Federation, Mrs Lynda Chalker, the
overseas development minister, said yesterday.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>62</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: N Ireland assessor
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
THE Northern Ireland Office has announced the setting up of an independent
assessor of the armed forces' complaints procedures in the province. Lord
Belstead, minister at the NIO, hoped the change would help the security
forces retain the confidence of both communities in Northern Ireland.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>63</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: British Coal profit
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
British Coal expects to show a 'modest bottom line profit' for the last
financial year, Mr Colin Moynihan, the junior energy minister, told the
Commons last night.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>64</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAE0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: Ingham as teaching aid rejected
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
A SUGGESTION that all new civil servants should be issued with a copy of Sir
Bernard Ingham's memoirs to learn how to 'stitch up elected ministers at the
request of the prime minister' was greeted with derision yesterday by Mr Tim
Renton, the Civil Service minister.
Mr Tony Banks, (Lab, Newham NW), had said Kill the Messenger, Sir Bernard's
account of 11 years as Mrs Margaret Thatcher's press secretary, would make
an effective teaching aid at the Civil Service College.
Earlier Mr Renton rejected a call by Mr Max Madden (Lab Bradford West) for a
new inquiry into the Westland affair.
In his book Sir Bernard denies that he authorised a leak from the department
of trade and industry of a letter from Sir Patrick Mayhew, the then
Solicitor General, referring to Mr Michael Heseltine's conduct throughout
the affair.
Observer, Page 18
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>65</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: Politicians play fast and loose
with the numbers / Testing the validity of arguments in the current debate
on taxes and public spending
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PHILIP STEPHENS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
WHEN politicians begin to argue about the relative merits of lower taxes or
higher public spending it is time for the voters to beware. When the debate
takes place in the approach to a general election and becomes enmeshed in
the detail of supposedly incontrovertible arithmetic the most sensible
course for the uncommitted is to suspend belief.
The real political - and economic - arguments behind the relative stances of
the Tories and Labour party in the past week have been drowned in a sea of
irreconcilable and often spurious statistics.
At one level there is no fundamental disagreement between the parties that
if the economy grows and tax rates remain constant, the government will reap
a 'growth dividend'. It can spend it in one of three ways, or in any
combination of the three: to reduce borrowing, to increase spending, and to
reduce tax rates.
The Conservative policy is based on delivering a combination of all three.
It says it will continue to provide real increases in resources for the
public sector, will move towards a balanced budget, and will find room to
cut the basic rate of income tax.
Labour has said it will use the dividend to boost spending and it will
definitely not cut tax rates. It has been silent on whether it would reduce
borrowing or keep it at present levels.
Its only costed spending commitments - to increase child benefit and raise
state pensions - will be financed separately by abolishing the ceiling on
employees National Insurance Contributions and by increasing the top rate of
income tax to 50p from 40p.
But if that sounds a relatively straightforward choice as between Labour and
the Conservatives, a dispassionate observer of the claims and counterclaims
flung across the party divide in recent days could draw only one conclusion:
our political masters canp. There have been many examples, but one or two
give some of the flavour.
In the middle of last week Mr Neil Kinnock, the Labour leader, declared that
on the basis of growth of 2.5 per cent a year his party could expect a
'dividend' of about Pounds 20bn to devote to public services over the
lifetime of a parliament. The Conservatives seized on the figure as a
'gaff'. Their own spending plans already included provision for an extra
Pounds 26bn in the next three years. If Labour was to spend Pounds 20bn more
it would have to raise taxes.
It was a credible, if contentious point but the Conservatives then spoilt
the case with their own arithmetic.
Their charge was that Labour would have to raise the basic rate of income
tax by 2p each and every year for the lifetime of a parliament, pushing the
basic rate of income tax to 35p. They omitted to mention that this would
raise not Pounds 20bn but Pounds 60bn. The message yesterday was that Mr
John Major, who first used the 10p figure, had made the 'reasonable'
assumption that Mr Kinnock had been talking about Pounds 20bn a year in
extra spending by the end of a parliament.
Labour meanwhile has been busy making its own assumptions about the
Conservatives' plans. The strategy behind its weekend charge that Mr Major
had a hidden agenda to raise Value Added Tax from 17.5 per cent to 22 per
cent in order to finance cuts in the basic rate of income tax was clear.
The government has raised VAT twice since 1979 to finance reductions in
income tax and, more recently, to reduce poll tax bills. Since its own
figures showed there was no room in the next three years to reduce the basic
rate of income tax, Labour felt able to claim that it was obvious VAT would
rise again.
Mr John Smith, the shadow chancellor, was careful, however, not to mention
any of the caveats with which Mr Norman Lamont, the chancellor, has
circumscribed the income tax commitment. A rise in VAT of 4.5 per cent would
raise Pounds 8bn a year, enough to cut 4p off the basic rate of tax in the
first budget of a new Conservative government.
Mr Lamont has stressed, however, that he plans to move towards his target at
an altogether more sedate pace.
Even if the politicians did not misinterpret their opponents' intentions,
the apparent precision of their figures bestows a spurious accuracy on
economic forecasts stretching five years ahead. The Treasury has shown in
the past few years that it is dangerous to trust predictions stretching just
12 months ahead.
The debate of the last few days does tell the voter that taxes are likely to
be lower under the Conservatives and public spending higher under Labour.
Beyond that the forecasts are perhaps best regarded with the same confidence
as the average horoscope.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11 Photograph Neil Kinnock, relying on annual growth of 2.5 per
cent to provide a Pounds 20bn 'dividend' (Omitted).
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>66</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: Plea for white collar jobless -
Unemployment
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By IVOR OWEN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
AS speculation about the date of the general election continued in the
Commons last night Sir Robert McCrindle, a senior Conservative backbencher,
called on the government to pay closer attention to the growth in 'white
collar' unemployment.
He stressed that it was a 'phenomenon' of the current recession which was
affecting voters in his Brentwood and Ongar constituency and others within
commuting distance who looked to the City of London for employment .
Labour MPs predicted that their party was poised to win the Monmouth
by-election on Thursday and that, as a result, Mr John Major, the prime
minister, would avoid calling a general election before October at the
earliest.
Mr John MacGregor, leader of the Commons, declined to comment on the timing
of the general election but reaffirmed the government's determination to
make Labour's spending commitments - and the implications for increased
taxation - a key feature of the campaign.
Sir Robert McCrindle accepted that priority had to be accorded to getting
inflation down but urged the government to spread the coverage of its
advertising campaign on unemployment to cover the services sector as well as
manufacturing industry.
While the 1980s had been characterised as the period of the 'yuppies' and,
perhaps, 'the unacceptable face of the City of London' the latest downturn
in the economy had changed the situation.
Sir Robert estimated that about 40 per cent of the current rise in
unemployment, and about half the company liquidations, were in the 'services
dominated' south east of England.
MPs approved a motion authoring the House to adjourn from May 23 to June 3
for the spring recess.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>67</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Parliament and Politics: Military shipments from Gulf will
be audited - Defence
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID WHITE, Defence Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE Ministry of Defence is organising a 'major audit effort' to prevent
fraud in the shipping of military equipment back from the Gulf, the Commons
Public Accounts Committee was told yesterday.
Sir Michael Quinlan, permanent under-secretary at the Ministry, said the aim
was to ensure it was returned 'in a properly accounted manner'.
His assurance followed a five-fold rise to Pounds 1.2m. in the amount
involved in alleged fraud at defence establishments in the last financial
year, compared with a total of just over Pounds 2m in the previous six
years.
He admitted he was surprised at the low proportion of people who were
dismissed or resigned as a result.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>68</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Unions seek advice on R-R jobs move
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL SMITH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
UNION LEADERS were yest-erday seeking legal advice over a decision by
Rolls-Royce to terminate the contracts of its 34,000 aerospace workers in
order to implement a pay freeze.
The move - claimed by some unions to be mass sackings, if only on a
temporary basis - is one of the most significant attempts by a company to
change its employees' contracts during the recession.
Rolls-Royce said the move was nothing more than a legal technicality, and
that employees would be offered contracts on broadly similar terms. It added
that it had no wish to see people dismiss themselves as a result of its
decision.
Mr Tim Webb, national officer of the MSF general technical union, said the
company had 'imposed a six-month wage freeze without consultation or
warning'.
Rolls-Royce announced the pay freeze last week at the same time as unveiling
plans to double job losses in the aerospace division this year to 6,000.
In a subsequent letter to employees, sent at the end of last week, the
company gave notice that contracts would be terminated at various stages,
depending on length of service, from last Saturday. New conditions would be
exactly the same as existing ones except that pay would be frozen.
Mr Webb said unions were worried the company was planning other changes to
working practices, including the introduction of individual contracts.
Few other companies among the increasing numbers of employers announcing pay
freezes have terminated existing contracts. However, Mr D'Arcy Payne,
personnel director in Rolls-Royce's aerospace division, said that the
company had taken careful legal advice before making its decision.
Under the pay freeze, increments to reward length of service will be
suspended. In addition, there will be no general pay rises for at least six
months.
Leaders of the manual workers' union will meet on Thursday to discuss the
job losses and the pay freeze, and union officials are also asking for a
meeting with the Rolls-Royce board.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>69</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Post Office staff vote for strike
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DIANE SUMMERS, Labour Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
COUNTER and clerical staff employed by the Post Office have voted to strike
over a 6.8 per cent pay offer. The Union of Communication Workers, the main
Post Office union, last night called for the urgent resumption of talks in
an attempt to have the offer increased.
The ballot result was announced yesterday at the UCW's conference in
Blackpool. Mr Alan Tuffin, UCW general secretary, agreed last night that the
result was some way from the overwhelming majority that union negotiators
had sought.
In a 67 per cent turnout for the ballot, 4,613 UCW members voted for
industrial action, while 3,732 voted against.
A total of 14,500 counter and clerical staff are employed by the Post Office
Counters business, which is separate from mail sorting and delivery service.
Mr Tuffin said that he would have liked more members to have taken part in
the ballot. However, the result, which had come from what was traditionally
a non-militant section of the union, indicated the strength of feeling among
the membership.
A number of options for action remained open, said Mr Tuffin. Workers in
cities such as London, Glasgow, Liverpool and Manchester were likely to have
voted most heavily for a strike, and it was possible there could be
selective action. He added that Post Office Counters management had been
asked to travel to Blackpool, where the union's conference continues for the
rest of the week, so that talks could re-open without delay.
Post Office Counters said last night that it was clear the union's executive
did not have an overwhelming mandate for strike action and it hoped that the
pay offer would now be quickly agreed.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>70</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Teachers strike
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
UP TO 1,000 teachers in Warwickshire are staging a one-day strike today in
protest at proposed teacher redundancies and cuts in the county's education
budget.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>71</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAETFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Co-operation on training urged
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
INDUSTRY training organisations, recognised by governments as the voice of
training for particular industries, were yesterday urged to act with
companies in their sectors to promote more effective training.
Mr Robert Jackson, a junior employment minister, made the appeal in his
endorsement of an action plan which was the result of a study of 10 ITOs by
Manpower Research on behalf of the Department of Employment and the National
Council of Industry Training Organisations.
ITO Network Review; NCITO, 5 George Lane, Royston, Herts; Free.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>72</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAESFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Nalgo leaders set deadline on dispute
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
LEADERS of unions representing 740,000 local government workers said
yesterday that an industrial dispute over pay was likely unless employers
made an offer before the end of the month.
Employers failed to make a pay offer yesterday, in spite of a claim of 12
per cent from unions led by the National and Local Government Officers
Association.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>73</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAERFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Three men win ruling on equal pensions
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
AN industrial tribunal has ruled that three men who left a Wigan engineering
company before the retirement age of 65 were entitled to the same pension as
women of their age.
The judgment reinforces others on equal pension ages.
The Equal Opportunities Commission said the judgment in the case against
Gullick Dobson showed again that sex discrimination in occupational pension
schemes was illegal because pensions must be considered as part of pay.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>74</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Harrods to be asked to abandon pay
freeze
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LISA WOOD, Labour Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
USDAW, the shop workers union, will this week attempt to persuade Harrods,
the London department store, to lift a six-month pay freeze for its 4,000
employees.
The Knightsbridge store, which has been encountering difficult trading
conditions because of a drop in tourist numbers after the Gulf war, has told
staff it will review the pay freeze, which started on April 1, in the
autumn.
Harrods, owned by House of Fraser, had offered its non-managerial staff a 3
per cent increase from April 1 with a further 2 per cent in October.
Usdaw, which will be meeting senior representatives of Harrods on Thursday
to ask them to re-open pay negotiations, said the offer was withdrawn on
Friday and a pay freeze announced. Last month Harrods told all its 600
managerial staff that their pay was being frozen.
Pay freezes have been adopted by a significant number of employers this year
but Laura Ashley Holdings, the fashion and household retailer, was so far
believed to be the only high-street retailer among them. Pay awards in the
retail sector have been averaging about 9 per cent to 10 per cent although
members of the Multiple Shoe Retailers' Association restricted pay rises for
19-to-21-year-olds to 5 per cent.
Earlier this year Harrods shed 200 staff. The redundancy programme was to
have been larger, but was trimmed after staff protests. It was prompted by
poor trading conditions in February.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>75</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): TUC finds few deals on recognition at
new plants
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GAPPER, Labour Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
UNIONS appear to have found it increasingly difficult in the past three
years to gain recognition agreements from inward investors and British
companies setting up new plants, a senior TUC official said yesterday.
Mr John Monks, TUC deputy general secretary, said only 10 deals had been
notified to the TUC since October 1988 under a procedure to regulate
inter-union conflict of the kind which led to the expulsion of the EETPU
electricians' union.
Under the prior-notification procedure, which was made permanent in June
last year, unions should tell the TUC about any single-union deal they are
about to sign.
Mr Monks told a conference in London that the number of deals was 'very
small' compared with the rush of agreements signed in the mid-1980s.
He added that the TUC might support establishing the size of union
membership in a company by a workforce ballot instead of a petition drawn up
by a union, saying this method might be 'politically advisable' in order to
gain public support for TUC proposals.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>76</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Non-managerial staff reject 5% Midland
offer
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DIANE SUMMERS, Labour Staff
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
MIDLAND BANK, the last of the big four clearing banks to enter pay
negotiations this year, has offered its 35,000 non-managerial staff a rise
of 5 per cent from June 1.
The offer was rejected by union negotiators and both sides will meet again
at the end of the week. Only a small improvement is expected on the offer,
and it is likely that the final settlement will fall at the lower end of
this year's likely 5-7 1/2 per cent range of pay increases for the clearers.
Midland's poor financial performance led it to halve its dividend earlier
this year.
Pressure on Midland's management to increase the offer will be reduced to
some extent by the June settlement date and what is expected to be a
continuing drop in inflation before then. The other main clearing banks' pay
increases take effect from February and April.
Mr Ed Sweeney, deputy general secretary elect of the Banking, Insurance and
Finance Union, said that Midland's negotiators had also drawn attention to
an offer of 5 per cent by Lloyds Bank to its 46,000 non-managerial staff.
Lloyds has said there is no further room for improvement on the offer,
although more talks are due to take place today.
Barclays' staff have already settled for a rise of more than 7 per cent and
NatWest has implemented a 7.5 per cent rise as part of a deal that will
allow the bank to require more flexible starting times from its employees.
Unions and management at TSB are also due to meet again at the end of the
week following an increase in the pay offer to staff from 6.75 per cent to 7
per cent.
Bifu members are being balloted on industrial action at Lombard North
Central. The National Union of Mineworkers has offered to back a recognition
claim by the banking union Bifu at the North of England Building Society by
urging NUM members to withdraw their savings from the society. Bifu has not
taken up the offer 'for the moment', it said, because the move could
threaten the livelihood of its members.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>77</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAENFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / UK News (Employment): Redundancies at American Express
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
AMERICAN Express has made 135 people redundant in the UK out of a total
workforce of 5,500. The company said the job cuts were necessary to manage
costs in a highly competitive environment.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>


<DOCNO>78</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BENBQAEMFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 91 / Hopes rise for the high street stock shop: NatWest's plans
to gear up for the widening of share ownership
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROLAND RUDD
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
NATIONAL Westminster knows better than most that timing is everything. The
bank has been pondering for sometime how to establish a new market for small
companies. It decided to push its proposal forward only when Mr Norman
Lamont, the chancellor, called for ideas on widening share ownership.
The London Stock Exchange was always going to pour cold water on the concept
of a rival market for small companies. Yesterday its chairman, Mr Andrew
Hugh Smith, could not resist asking just how NatWest thought it could find
buyers for shares in tiny businesses.
As he sees it, it is one thing to buy shares from Mrs Brown in Newcastle but
it is another to sell them to Mr Jones in Truro. Just who wants shares in
penny-halfpenny companies? As far as the stock exchange is concerned, there
is no way of answering the question, which is why there is no rival market.
NatWest disagrees. It believes there are two possible solutions: it could
establish a group of independent agents tied to NatWest, specialising in
small companies and buying shares from individual investors; or it could
link with a third party acting as a broker marketing shares acquired by
NatWest.
Since the demise of the Third Market at the end of last year, the bank's
stockbrokers have been convinced that they could offer those companies a new
home.
It also believes it could pick up unlisted businesses, which typically have
1m shares at Pounds 1 each, as well as some of the smaller companies quoted
on the Unlisted Securities Market.
The USM was set up on November 10 1980 to provide a separately regulated and
more flexible market for smaller companies.
NatWest believes it could offer many of the smaller USM-quoted companies
easier access to the public at an earlier stage of their development.
NatWest established a share dealing service in December 1986, for the
privatisation of British Gas and it has been thinking of ways of developing
its service.
In January 1988 it extended its touch-screen share-dealing operation
throughout the country. In 278 of the bank's 2,900 branches, investors can
buy or sell shares in 550 companies.
In spite of the operation's initial success, the branches do an average of
only 10 deals a day each.
Mr Neil Stapley, managing director of NatWest Stockbrokers, assigned a
project team to look at ways to extend that service. The team calculated
that a market for small companies would be relatively cheap to establish.
When the Treasury issued a press release in March asking for ideas to sell
the shares it owns in BT, NatWest Stockbrokers seized on a supplementary
question. The chancellor wanted to know how high-street share shops could
develop throughout the country - he was not interested just in the BT sale
but in widening share ownership generally.
That was good enough for NatWest. It is relying on the Treasury to keep to
its side of the deal and will come up with the ideas if Whitehall throws its
weight behind them in the face of stock exchange hostility.
To be fair to Mr Hugh Smith, he has made it clear that the bank is in an
ideal situation to establish a market in small shares. If it decides to set
up a rival market, Mr Hugh Smith does not think it should necessarily be
judged as a challenge to the exchange. Others are not so sure.
Mr Brian Winterflood, managing director of Winterflood Securities, which
offers a share service in 830 small companies, said NatWest had
'state-of-the-art' technology to offer a first-rate market for small
companies.
'It has the capability to challenge the stock exchange,' he said.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 8
</PAGE>


</DOC>